Grow Data Skills: Hello, everyone. Good morning.
Grow Data Skills: A very good morning to all of you.
Grow Data Skills: Hey, good morning, Akul.
Grow Data Skills: Morning Seph, Morning Path, Morning Shrijan, Shobadi, Anand, Shantanu.
Grow Data Skills: Bhavna, Shev, Ayush… Priyanshu, the… Monish, Ravi…
Grow Data Skills: Very, very good morning to all of you, very good morning to all of you.
Grow Data Skills: Quick check. I hope I'm audible clearly, my video is fine.
Grow Data Skills: Cool, awesome, thanks for confirming that.
Grow Data Skills: So I'll just take one more minute, let other people also join, and then after one minute, we'll get started. I'll just take a starting first 5 minutes just to set up the tone for this entire bootcamp, although I have created one induction session for you. If you haven't seen it, you haven't checked it out.
Grow Data Skills: Not a problem. After today's session, you can just watch it. It is already there in your course content, right? It is uploaded there. Where I have already described each and everything, that how we are going to flow in this bootcamp.
Grow Data Skills: how you are going to access your content, how you are going to get everything, okay? The entire flow, everything I have step-by-step explained there, okay? But again, today I'll take a starting 5 minutes, just to welcome you all and set up the entire tone for this, bootcamp, so that we all are on the same page.
Grow Data Skills: And yeah, meanwhile, can you let me know from which part of India, or maybe outside India you guys are joining from?
Grow Data Skills: So it will give me clarity… The diversity here.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, Pune, Chennai, Lucknow. I'm also from Lucknow, my native place is Lucknow.
Grow Data Skills: Bangalore, Hyderabad, Nepal… Bangalore. Awesome. Delhi, Chennai, Haryana.
Grow Data Skills: Currently, Jawalpur… Okay, awesome, awesome.
Grow Data Skills: Sweden.
Grow Data Skills: Nice.
Grow Data Skills: U.S.
Grow Data Skills: Pune… okay, that's awesome, that's awesome.
Grow Data Skills: Great, great. Texas, Pune, Kolkata… Cool. So, folks are from India, outside India as well, that's great.
Grow Data Skills: All right, cool. I think, we can get it started now. So, first of all, I would like to welcome you all who has taken part in this complete AI Data Engine with Bootcamp, with AWS Bootcamp, and…
Grow Data Skills: Next 4 months are going to be very, very exciting. I am hopeful that you guys have gone through the entire curriculum, etc, and I…
Grow Data Skills: actually put good amount of effort to make that kind of curriculum, right? Because if you guys are following me for…
Grow Data Skills: maybe quite some time, myself, Sashang Mishra, and having more than 10 years of experience in the data engineering space, okay? And, on Guru Data Skills for the last 3 years.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? You can say…
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, very less marketing. I mean, we are not doing it, because, whoever is becoming part of the Grow Data Skills, it's all about based on the personal experience, and, you can say the word of mouth, which is
Grow Data Skills: the good USB we have. So, yeah, talking about the programs I have been trying to create, it's all through my practical knowledge, okay?
Grow Data Skills: And I have also made a recent… like, I have made one… another job switch. I haven't announced which company I have joined and not, okay? So, for last 2 months, regressively, I have seen that
Grow Data Skills: how companies are testing the data engineers, how the data engineering profile, not massively, but slowly, gradually, a lot of roles are turning into the AI data engineer. And when you are going into the interviews, when you are serving in any company as a data engineer.
Grow Data Skills: Then, what is expected from core data engineering perspective, and what is expected
Grow Data Skills: like, from your side to know with regards to the AI aspects, right? Be it RAG, be it MCPs, agents, bit of understanding of the LLM. So this entire course, I am going to, first of all, keep very, very practical, right, and entirely project-driven, so that you're actually learning by implementing the things, not just slideshows or the theoretical aspects, right? Wherever it will come up.
Grow Data Skills: I will already provide that beforehand so that you can go through it, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, that is how it is going to be. So now, at least for next 4 months, I just want you guys to have a trust and faith in me that
Grow Data Skills: whatever I'm going to cover, it's all because of my practical experience, right? I have worked with very good companies, I have seen their process, the way I've…
Grow Data Skills: design and, like, created the various data solutions for various data domains. So I am going to put all my brain here, I'm going to put all my practical learning, so you will be learning with that same vision itself, okay?
Grow Data Skills: Now… For the next 4 months, I want you guys to be very serious.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Serious with respect to the consistency, first of all, not leaving anything in between, and, like…
Grow Data Skills: cover it up, okay? Because data engineering is a little bit vast, okay, with respect to the tech stack, with respect to the versatility, right? A lot of things need to be learned. So, be serious for next 4 months, because after that, you are going to have really, really good results, okay?
Grow Data Skills: complete, in-depth knowledge about the core data engineering, AWS, and the AI aspects.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: And, be very, very consistent. Whatever you are going to get from the, maybe, class notes, the assignments, quizzes, etc, be very serious about it, right? Just prepare it accordingly.
Grow Data Skills: And…
Grow Data Skills: I just want to, like, call out one more important thing, and then we can simply jump straight to our… today's agenda.
Grow Data Skills: That is.
Grow Data Skills: when I'm actually teaching, right, I love to maintain some momentum, and I hope you guys can understand it, right? If someone is teaching, and maybe I'm getting interrupted every 2 minutes or something, that will break the momentum. So…
Grow Data Skills: I have opened the chat, you guys can interact with, right, each other. If you have any questions, you can exchange with, each other.
Grow Data Skills: But, related to the class topic, whenever I will see a very important question in the chat, I will instantly answer that, okay? Rest, after the class completion, we will have a dedicated time for the doubts session, where I will ask you guys to raise your hands, and you can ask your doubts. I will unmute you, okay? So, with that patience, with that clarity, just… we will be moving ahead so that you are getting maximum outcome from
Grow Data Skills: this single session, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So I hope, you are clear with it. So, obviously, today's session, we are going to get started with the SQL, okay? And step by step, we will be touching upon the every single aspect of it, right? So here, again, I'm not going to teach someone the entire DBMS or databases, because the
Grow Data Skills: course module is SQL, right? That if you already have the databases.
Grow Data Skills: then how you are going to use SQL, how you are going to master the every basic, medium, and advanced level concept of it, so that when you are going into the interviews, or when you are working as a data engineer, how you are going to apply those logics. If a complex problem statement has given to you, how you are going to break it down in the pieces, and going to write a proper SQL query for your
Grow Data Skills: analytical problem for your ingestion problem, whatever it is. Okay?
Grow Data Skills: Cool.
Grow Data Skills: So, let's get it started now. That's the only thing I just wanted to let you know in the beginning.
Grow Data Skills: Cool. So, the very first thing we are going to talk about is…
Grow Data Skills: the databases part, okay? Because we are going to talk about the SQL, so…
Grow Data Skills: at least for next 4 to 5 minutes, we should understand that where this SQL is going to come into the picture itself, right? I will also touch base on the weightage of SQL when you are going to appear into the interviews. Again, it's, like, based on… based on my interview experiences so far.
Grow Data Skills: in the 10 years of, timeline, plus my recent interview experiences as well. For the last 2 months, where I interviewed at Atlassian, Uber, right, Databricks, good startups, okay, mid-scale startups, so I will explain you based on that experience as well.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, first of all, what is database, right? Because this term, SQL, is
Grow Data Skills: Like, tightly coupled with that term itself, the database.
Grow Data Skills: So.
Grow Data Skills: in the big data ecosystem, right, data is actually everything for you. Whatever you are building the data pipeline to move data from point X to point Y, that is something, right, where this entire
Grow Data Skills: data keyword is coming into the picture. It's all about the data analysis, you are taking the business decisions, you are creating the AI applications on top of it, doing any sort of analysis. So this keyword, right?
Grow Data Skills: Now, what is database? Whenever you are talking about these data, right, in practical, you have also seen it, okay? If you, like, if you are using Excel, you have some sort of
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: Like.
Grow Data Skills: are we supposed to do hands-on along with you? You can do that, right? Not a problem, but in the class, I recommend that don't take notes, etc, because everything I'm going to provide, the script, command, etc, everything will be getting. So focus more on the understanding part, how things are going on.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so…
Grow Data Skills: What is the database? It is the structured and organized set of the data, right? If you have worked with Excel, right.
Grow Data Skills: there you have created the rows and columns, you are doing some data entry. So, if you talk about Excel, that is also a kind of software application which is allowing you to put some data there, and then you are doing something something. But when we talk about the database, it's a very generic term, right, where you…
Grow Data Skills: Basically, organize your data in some structured format.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, that is your database. Now, if I have to talk, I'll also keep on sharing my screen, where I will write it so that you have a better clarity.
Grow Data Skills: And then we'll simply jump onto the practical writing SQL. When I will be creating the databases, we'll be doing the operations, then you will have a better clarity, okay? I hope my notepad screen is visible as well, you guys able to see it.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, as I said about the database, So, this is generic keyword.
Grow Data Skills: like… Structured and organized set of the data.
Grow Data Skills: and organized.
Grow Data Skills: Organized set of…
Grow Data Skills: data, okay? Cool. Now, when you talk about the, my notepad screen is not visible. Okay, sorry, I think I forgot to share my screen, yeah.
Grow Data Skills: Cool. Nothing, I haven't, wrote, like, a lot of things, just a same problem statement I'm talking about, okay? So, database, like, a structured and organized set of the data.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Now, when you talk about the database.
Grow Data Skills: Right? The very important term here is this thing.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, there are two types of the databases as well. One is the… Relational… And, second is the…
Grow Data Skills: NoSQL, okay? So this NoSQL category part, right.
Grow Data Skills: So, we will try to first understand, like, when you will understand the difference between the RDBMS, etc, then I will come onto this part one more time.
Grow Data Skills: And we'll explain this thing, okay? So databases, we talked about it, and coming on to the… this part. There is one more important thing to understand here, which is DBMS.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, what is DBMS? Now, this is the part where you…
Grow Data Skills: I have actually used it practically, okay? When you take a name off that I have worked on MySQL, I have worked on Postgres, I have worked on Oracle, I have worked on MSSQL, right?
Grow Data Skills: So, when you are actually taking these names, right, these… these are what? These are actually your DBMS, right? DBMS stands for Database Management, right, System. So…
Grow Data Skills: when you have to describe it technically, so those software applications, which allows you to manage and manipulate the data, that is what you call the DBMS.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, if you have worked with MySQL, right, so what you are doing is, either you are operating maybe through some
Grow Data Skills: IDE, or you have written some…
Grow Data Skills: application through APIs, you are talking to the databases, right? Or you might have written some Java program, Python program, connecting to the database, and doing some sort of operations there, right? Maybe loading the data and reading the data. This is what generally we are doing.
Grow Data Skills: And when you talk about the data engineering, right, the whole ecosystem.
Grow Data Skills: You will see databases on both the ads, right? Many times you are reading from the databases, many of times you are dumping the data into the databases. But when you talk about the software applications in general, right? The Amazon, let's say, these are the applications, if you're
Grow Data Skills: accessing it through web, mobile, like, Netflix, etc, etc. Any web application, if you are talking about.
Grow Data Skills: Right? At least they have some sort of backend.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Where you have written some APIs, etc. And whatever activity as a user you are doing, maybe creating the account, doing some purchase, right? Everything is going to be maintained, because that is the data.
Grow Data Skills: for the Amazon, for Netflix, whatever you are doing, that is the data. So, that is going to be managed somewhere. So, in order to manage your data, you need a database, okay? So, database is the generic term, coming onto the DBMS part.
Grow Data Skills: database management system. So, it is a software application to manage and manipulate data. Means.
Grow Data Skills: It will give you all the functionalities, right, to ingest the data. It will give you everything, right? To query the data, read it, manipulate it.
Grow Data Skills: everything you'll be able to do with that. And that is what your DBM is.
Grow Data Skills: DVMSS.
Grow Data Skills: Software app, 2… Manage… And… Manipulate data.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? And don't worry about these rough notes, it is just, I'm using to explain you the things. There's these technical definition terms, I have just curated in 4-5 PDF pages, so that you can refer it anytime, just for the technical differences, right? I will give that to you, but just try to understand the terminologies I'm talking about.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Now, when you talk about the DBMS, okay? So, here, inside that, you simply talk about the RDBMS, okay? So, RDBMS stands for Relational Database Management System.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, DBMS, software application, it's a, again, generic word for all…
Grow Data Skills: the other type of the databases as well, not just the, like, RDBMS, but all other type of the databases where you are calling it the software application to manage the data and manipulate it.
Grow Data Skills: But when we talk about the RDBMS specifically, then things start changing slightly, okay? So, again, RDBMS…
Grow Data Skills: And this is the part I was talking about here, RDBMS.
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Grow Data Skills: Cool.
Grow Data Skills: So…
Grow Data Skills: This is also a software application where you can store the data, manage it, and query it, like, reading the data, and also.
Grow Data Skills: retrieve the structured data, right? Organize into the tables. This is the part, like, where you're…
Grow Data Skills: very typical terms of the databases comes into the picture, that I have created a table, I have inserted one row there, right? These are the columns into the table, and we can query it, okay? So, when you talk about the RDBMS, so structured data organized into the tables, and
Grow Data Skills: Table is an entity which basically consists rows and columns.
Grow Data Skills: And why we are calling it the Relational Database, or the RDBMS, because in the RDBMS, you can create multiple tables, right? And these tables
Grow Data Skills: may and may not get connected, or may get linked with each other based on some specific identifiers. And that is what we known as the primary key and foreign key, right? Multiple times, you would have heard those terms, and I will explain it with a simple example as well.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, if you have to call it RDBMS, again, software app.
Grow Data Skills: to… Manage Data.
Grow Data Skills: Right? And what we can say here?
Grow Data Skills: is structured…
Grow Data Skills: organized… data in… tables… Form.
Grow Data Skills: Which… Me?
Grow Data Skills: Link with each other.
Grow Data Skills: Based on…
Grow Data Skills: keys, okay? So, when we will be practically implementing these things, right? So, I will explain this concept of the primary key, foreign key, you will see them working practically, okay? So.
Grow Data Skills: Now, this is the part, right? The RDBMS, NoSQL. So, when I was saying that I have worked with MySQL, Postgres, Oracle, so they are actually your RDBMS, okay? So, if I have to list down here…
Grow Data Skills: MySQL, right? When you talk about the examples of it, MySQL, Postgres.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Oracle. So these are what? These are your relational databases, because these are the software applications. So when you say MySQL,
Grow Data Skills: Right? A lot of time, people say, okay, I have used MySQL as a database, which is definitely right term to use, because database is the main generic starting keyword and the term, but very technically, if you have to explain someone, so MySQL, Postgres, Crackle, this is actually the RDBMS. They are, like, a proper software application, a set of program.
Grow Data Skills: Right? You basically set up the MySQL database somewhere, maybe in your local, maybe on some cloud, etc, and then you start ingesting the data into it and retrieving the data from it.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So…
Grow Data Skills: when you are running something, okay, insert the data and read the data. So, in the backend of the MySQL itself, that is some set of program which is allowing you to store the data somewhere, okay? And then, similarly, reading it.
Grow Data Skills: So, that is the main point to understand. These are the IDBMS because they allow you to store the data in a tabular structure, right? And…
Grow Data Skills: The tabular structure means the data in the form of rows and columns.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? And when you talk about the NoSQL databases, that is a very broader topic itself, and once we will reach onto Module 3 or 4, I guess, where we have discussed about the MongoDB and the NoSQL database, so there we will deep dive into it. There are various types of the NoSQL databases. What is NoSQL database, like MongoDB, Cassandra, ScyllaDB, right?
Grow Data Skills: and many others, okay? So, each of the NoSQL database has
Grow Data Skills: a different style of storing the data, and based on that one, we take a decision, right? Whenever we are doing some system design, or the pipeline architecture design, so we take a decision based on the business use case and the actual requirement, that whether we should go ahead with the Mongo, or Cassandra, or Scylla, or any other
Grow Data Skills: NoSQL database, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, we will come onto this one later point, when we will reach on that module.
Grow Data Skills: So, now, this is the part, right? We talked about the RDBMS, so you understood. So, from now onwards, you are going to call it in that way, MySQL, Postgres, Oracle, these are your RDBMS. So, very simple example, right? Let's say this is my SQL.
Grow Data Skills: Right?
Grow Data Skills: Wherever it is hosted, we will
Grow Data Skills: talk about it. So, in the MySQL, what you are simply saying, that…
Grow Data Skills: we store the data in the structured format, okay? So, here, imagine…
Grow Data Skills: very simple and basic example you must have seen, right? The, employee and the department type of the data, okay? So, storing the employee data. Employees might have, various informations.
Grow Data Skills: like, the… every employee has a unique ID, their address, their date of birth, etc, okay? So, here, let's say this is your…
Grow Data Skills: employee table, and when you talk about the RDBMS and the tabular data, so eventually, in the rows and the column format, you store the data.
Grow Data Skills: And this is another table.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so here, employee ID, and maybe name, let's say, and the department ID.
Grow Data Skills: This is Employee Table.
Grow Data Skills: And this is department table.
Grow Data Skills: So here, we have the department ID and department name.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so this one…
Grow Data Skills: Let's say 1, 2, 3, name is ABC, and here we have this department, let's say…
Grow Data Skills: Department ID 100, department ID 200, Department ID 300. This is IT department, this is HR department, this is finance department.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so this is the one, let's say… You can see.
Grow Data Skills: 100.
Grow Data Skills: 100 and 200.
Grow Data Skills: So now, if you look at these two tables, right, if you look at these two tables, this is your employee table and the department table, correct? So, these are your columns, okay, and this is your, actually, data row.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? This is your column, and this is your row. Same is happening here. And if we focus on this specific term, right, which may link with each other based on keys, okay? So, when…
Grow Data Skills: you are actually looking at this data from the naked eyes, because it is visible to you, right? You are able to see that, oh, there is a column named department ID, which is mentioned in the employee table, and that column is also mentioned here. And I can visibly see these values are also very much similar.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So, this is actually a kind of relation which is being built here based on this specific column, right? Because directly, indirectly, this column from the department table is being referred into the employee table.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, what is the kind of relation you are building here? That employees are working in the departments, right? Employees are working in some sort of departments, correct?
Grow Data Skills: So, this is the part where primary key, foreign key, those concepts will come into the picture. So, when I will start creating the table, when I will be putting some constraint, I will help you to understand these things in much more detail, right? What is primary key, how does it work, what is foreign key, how does it work, how we implement it, but I just created these two tables to help you understand
Grow Data Skills: that when you are talking about the RDB MS, how the tables look like, obviously in the form of the rows and the columns.
Grow Data Skills: And this is how you are able to see the linking and the relationship between the two tables, or more than two tables.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, just for the basic understanding, this is pretty much good enough.
Grow Data Skills: Now, our main topic is the SQL, okay? So, what is actually SQL now? So, let's take a step back and talk with respect to the programming languages only, okay? I'm…
Grow Data Skills: maybe I'm assuming here that many of you might have worked with the different programming languages, Python, Java, Scala, C++, at any point of time. Okay? So…
Grow Data Skills: Programming language.
Grow Data Skills: When you are writing a program, so actually what you are doing, you are writing some set of instructions, which is going to get executed on some user-provided input data.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? And each language has its own format, right? Maybe the syntax.
Grow Data Skills: Java has a different syntax, Python has a different syntax, but ultimately, you are solving a common purpose with all these programming languages, which is what? Talking to the machine, right? If you have your…
Grow Data Skills: Desktop, laptop, whatever it is. You are writing the program, basically, to talk to the machine.
Grow Data Skills: to give the instructions to your machine itself that I have received this input data from the user. Based on these instructions, please manipulate it and give me some output.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, programming language is a way to communicate with your machine.
Grow Data Skills: In a similar way, when you talk about the databases, right, again.
Grow Data Skills: RDBMS, or any NoSQL database, if you take a name of that, right? So, in that case, what you are doing?
Grow Data Skills: Right? You have your…
Grow Data Skills: like, RDBMS, those software applications, which allowed you to store the data, and they also allow you to manipulate the data.
Grow Data Skills: So, when you talk about SQL, so SQL stands for Structured Query Language, right? A structured query language means
Grow Data Skills: the set of statements, right? Set of statements.
Grow Data Skills: to communicate with your data, right? So, programming language, set of instructions to communicate with your machine to process some user-provided input data. Similarly, SQL, you can…
Grow Data Skills: For very simplistic understanding, you can say another programming language which allows us to interact with the data
Grow Data Skills: which is stored in any kind of the database. RDBMS, NoSQL, whatever it is. So, SQL is a very common layer, right? SQL is a very common layer. It will keep on changing. Database to database type, few things will keep on changing, but the
Grow Data Skills: top-layer abstraction is completely same, right? Even if you're working with MongoDB till some extent, Cassandra, accessing it, maybe via some JDBC connection, or via some workbench, DBWeaver, or through CLI, whatever it is.
Grow Data Skills: till some extent, they will allow you to query the data. Again, following the same pattern, the SQL pattern.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so SQL is what? Another programming language to work with the data which is stored in the database. So, what can change here? So, when you're talking about the MySQL, there will be few
Grow Data Skills: things which will be different, right? Because…
Grow Data Skills: when you individually talk about the different database, MySQL, Postgres, Oracle, so…
Grow Data Skills: with respect to the SQL, right, there are a lot of things which are already pre-built. The inbuilt functions, right? Let's say there is a column which is of the data type, and you want to extract the year component from that one. So there are inbuilt functions created for the same. Similarly.
Grow Data Skills: there are mathematical functions created, the sum, main, max, average. So, when you talk about different databases, so there, time to time, you will see slight changes.
Grow Data Skills: Not the entire SQL query pattern, but slight changes with respect to the functions.
Grow Data Skills: And few other things, okay? So that is how it is going to be. So, in our bootcamp, we are going to focus on MySQL, okay? And what I can say, based on my personal experience, if you…
Grow Data Skills: In the interviews, right? When you appear in the interviews, no one force you to write it in any specific syntax, okay?
Grow Data Skills: You are very comfortable to go ahead with any kind of syntax, and let's say, just giving you the example, that there are a lot of functions, inbuilt functions, right? And no one can memorize each and everything, right? You basically try to…
Grow Data Skills: learn the various patterns of solving the SQL problems, right? Using the joins, let's say, group by window functions, which we will be, like, practically implementing.
Grow Data Skills: But when you go into the interviews.
Grow Data Skills: Right? If you don't remember any syntax, any of the syntax, so interviewers are always helpful enough that either you can Google the syntax, right? If not, you can just write any generic term for that one, right? If you're writing the SQL query statements, etc. Okay?
Grow Data Skills: So that is how it works, and you don't need to memorize each and every thing there, that's what I can say.
Grow Data Skills: Alright. So, moving on to the, like, SQL part.
Grow Data Skills: now…
Grow Data Skills: before starting with the practical part, I just want to highlight the importance of it. So, as I said.
Grow Data Skills: you are actually targeting such kind of job role, the data engineering, right? Where your main responsibility is to
Grow Data Skills: obviously, create these scalable data pipelines. And when we create these scalable data pipelines, right, so source could be the database as well, from where you need to fetch the data, and the target could be another database as well, where you need to ingest the data, right? And…
Grow Data Skills: not only data engineers are using SQL. It is used by each and every one, but when you talk about the data domain, here SQL is being used very, very extensively, right? So when you talk about the data analyst, right, that is… the SQL is bread and butter for them.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Because they are the one who are going to…
Grow Data Skills: basically show the business insights to the end stakeholders. They are going to create the dashboards. So.
Grow Data Skills: whatever data, let's say this data itself, which you are seeing here, you created some ingestion pipeline, and maybe in some MySQL, you have just dumped this particular data. Now.
Grow Data Skills: Basically, there is a data analyst who want to create a dashboard that how many employees are there in each individual department.
Grow Data Skills: So this is a simple problem statement.
Grow Data Skills: You have your employee data, you have your department data. And the problem data analysts want to solve
Grow Data Skills: I need to count that in each department, how many employees are there.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So how he is going to do that? He's simply going to run some logical statements on this particular table.
Grow Data Skills: Right? That…
Grow Data Skills: grouping all these departments, individual departments together, and taking the count of the employees. That is the kind of thing he wants to solve. So he need to write a SQL query for that one.
Grow Data Skills: Right? You need to write a proper SQL statement, which will be running against this particular table in the database, and you'll be getting the output for the same.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So… I'm now talking about the importance of your SQL.
Grow Data Skills: Right? In your interviews. So, based on all my interview experiences, I always give 30% to 40% weightage to the SQL. Okay? No matter how
Grow Data Skills: how good you are with all your data engineering understanding, how amazing projects you have built, and how much technical, in-depth knowledge you have about Spark, Databricks, Snowflake, Airflow, whatever it is.
Grow Data Skills: But still, even I'm talking with respect to 10 years of data engineering experience, even if you're going ahead with this experience in top product-based companies.
Grow Data Skills: in two rounds, right? First round for sure, then second round, it could be, I mean, the next round where you can be tested for SQL again, it could be second or third again, right? So, when you talk about the interview process of product-based companies, so…
Grow Data Skills: they have a dedicated round for the data warehouse modeling, okay? Data warehouse modeling, where they ask you to design a data model, and based on that one.
Grow Data Skills: he might give you some business KPIs. For that, you need to write the SQL queries. So, again, your SQL will be tested there, but in first technical round, you will be heavily tested on the
Grow Data Skills: like SQL. Recently, I shared my experience for the Uber as well. So, in the first round, he asked.
Grow Data Skills: the dedicated SQL question.
Grow Data Skills: And then, in the third round, okay, he again asked 3 SQL questions dedicately, and there was a second round, which eventually became the data warehouse modeling. So, after creating the data model, I had to write the SQL query for the 2 business KPIs the interviewer gave me.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, that is why I'm telling you, be it Google, Amazon, Microsoft, Uber, Atlassian, Walmart, any type of good product-based companies, even service-based or consulting, SQL plays a very, very important role. If you are not good at this side and have mastered everything about data engineering.
Grow Data Skills: So, cracking these technical interview rounds will be a little bit challenging for you, right?
Grow Data Skills: And with respect to SQL, the questions will always be around the medium to hard category. When I say medium, so very common things like joins, aggregates, group by, etc, but when we come onto the advanced part, so window functions, frame clause, conditional aggregates, right, CTs, these things will come into the picture.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, that's why I'm telling you, this is a very, very important module, and very important thing. So, in this module itself, I will be touching upon all those important, like, the topics
Grow Data Skills: right, of the SQL, and practically solving them with some type of interview questions, so that you are able to relate and build the logic. And I will give you a good
Grow Data Skills: preparation guide as well, where I have already documented very good amount of questions across different categories, easy, medium, hard, so that you can practice SQL more and more. So, a lot of time, people ask me that I…
Grow Data Skills: how can I master SQL, right? So there is no shortcut for it, to be very honest. The very first layer to master SQL is whether you have mastered every single concept of it, right? If you know about the various window functions.
Grow Data Skills: Do you actually know where to apply it by reading the problem statement? If you have figured out that thing, you will be able to break down any complex SQL problem in the smaller pieces, and you will be able to write a perfect query for that.
Grow Data Skills: That I can say it. I have also mastered it over the period of time. I did not master it maybe in 2 months, 4 months, or something, right? It was all about the practice.
Grow Data Skills: how much practice you are doing for the same, and when you are working in the industrial projects, what other, best practices you are seeing with respect to the SQL, right? So, that is how I can say it. So, one personal experience I want to share. So, when I was working at Paytm.
Grow Data Skills: So, I was very closely working with the data analysts and these people. And one thing I can definitely say, these guys are damn good on the SQL side.
Grow Data Skills: So back in 2019, I was not having that much confidence in the SQL, so whenever I had a chance to work with the data analysts of that particular project or something, I always looked at their way of writing the SQLs, and I asked them those kind of curious questions that, why you are doing this and that. So that also gives you good insights.
Grow Data Skills: So, why I'm sharing this experience, if you're also in such kind of ecosystem, working with those people whose
Grow Data Skills: Bread and butter is SQL, so have a, like, spend some time with them closely, and always seek that kind of knowledge, that how you are doing it, what is the purpose of it, so you will definitely learn a lot of good things about the SQL. So, it's all about personal experience.
Grow Data Skills: Okay. So, now let's get started with the setup part, right? That what we are going to set up, and most importantly, understand that how our local setup is going to work, right, for which I will walk you through with the steps.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: And don't get confused if you are looking at my notebook, right, and you are getting confused with this Tuesday, 9, and this time. So there is some glitch with my notebook, right? Today is obviously the 20th of June, not 9th of January.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, coming on to this part, the setup.
Grow Data Skills: So I'll show you the setup, but before that, I want to talk about this thing.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So we talked about the MySQL, okay? This is your RDBMS.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, let's first understand, with respect to,
Grow Data Skills: the production grade of standards, right? So, you must have heard that your team lead is saying that, hey, Sashank, I have, set up one MySQL database on AWS, now you can use that, okay? He just said that part. So, what does it actually mean? So, MySQL is a RDBMS, a particular
Grow Data Skills: Application. Software application.
Grow Data Skills: And in order to run the software application, what do you need?
Grow Data Skills: My question to all of you, in order to run any software application, bare minimum, what do you need?
Grow Data Skills: You need environment, server, compute.
Grow Data Skills: Understood. So this is a very right term to use, machine, compute, right? Infrastructure. This is something which is pretty much needed. ID, client, these things are the GUI, or the interface from where you are going to interact with that. But when we talk about the
Grow Data Skills: IDBMS or something, this is a software application, and in order to run it, you need a machine.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So… So, here, imagine that This is your…
Grow Data Skills: AWS.
Grow Data Skills: AWS Cloud.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? And my team, as I said, my tech lead, what he said, Sushang, I have created one MySQL instance, okay, on the AWS. So, creating the MySQL instance, what he actually meant, that there is a machine, right, of
Grow Data Skills: some configuration, because when you talk about a machine or a commodity hardware, right, on the cloud, so it will have the CPU,
Grow Data Skills: Right? The processing unit, it will have the memory, right? It will have the network bandwidth, right? So when my team lead said that I have created one MySQL instance, so means he has set up one machine where MySQL is actually running.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, if I have to say it this way…
Grow Data Skills: That he has set up one machine.
Grow Data Skills: machine, server, whatever you want to call, okay? And this particular machine, right, a typical machine. The way you are… the way you look at your laptop, that is also a machine. It has a processing unit, it has the memory, right? And obviously the network, etc. And similarly, if you are using desktop.
Grow Data Skills: Anything, that is also a machine.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, this machine has the CPU… Sorry, processing unit.
Grow Data Skills: Memory?
Grow Data Skills: Network bandwidth.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, MySQL.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So this is the machine, and
Grow Data Skills: MySQL is…
Grow Data Skills: Running.
Grow Data Skills: Here. Okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, this is your MySQL, as I said, this is your machine and everything, because…
Grow Data Skills: when I was saying this thing, that…
Grow Data Skills: You have an employee table, you have a department table, correct?
Grow Data Skills: So, how you are going to do that, okay? So…
Grow Data Skills: The very first thing is, you are going to create a table, right?
Grow Data Skills: Create table.
Grow Data Skills: So, what does create table mean here? So, create table means creating the blueprint, right? If you go back to the previous
Grow Data Skills: right, this part. Here, you can see that this is an employee table. Employee table, right, has these 3 columns.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, this is the part I'm talking about here, that whenever you are going to work with the databases, right, and specifically for the data storage and manipulation part, the very first thing is, you are going to do create table, which is the blueprint
Grow Data Skills: off.
Grow Data Skills: blueprint.
Grow Data Skills: So this is the blueprint of the structure, right? That how you are going to store the data in that particular table. How many columns are going to be there? And each column will be having its type, because some value could be of integer, some value could be of the double, some could be of date.
Grow Data Skills: Right? In that way, different, different values could be there.
Grow Data Skills: So, once your table is created, the second step is this.
Grow Data Skills: Right?
Grow Data Skills: Ingest or load data, basically.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So, after creating the table, right, after creating the table, when you are loading the data, so what I said, this is actually your machine. So, when you are writing the data, where it is getting written, it is actually getting written into the memory
Grow Data Skills: that particular machine is providing you, correct? So that is what I'm saying, when…
Grow Data Skills: in the production terms, when you're talking about there is a Postgres instance, there is a MySQL instance, means you have a database, right? Obviously, that is an application itself, which is running on a machine, so when you are writing the data, that data is actually getting written here.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So if you divide it or call it as a memory part, so that data is actually getting written here, in the memory of that particular machine itself, right? So, that is why, whenever you talk about the instances, that I have created one MySQL instance, Postgres instance.
Grow Data Skills: So, you always configure this thing, right? That what capacity you are expecting from your instance, right? If over the period of time, you are expecting huge amount of data is going to be there, so you definitely try to pick that kind of machine which is big in size, in terms of memory, in terms of processing unit itself, so that you can store
Grow Data Skills: the good amount of the data there over the period of time, right? That is what
Grow Data Skills: The particular instance set up on any of the cloud.
Grow Data Skills: Now, when you have this particular machine running in.
Grow Data Skills: Correct. So now, obviously, when you are talking about the production application, let's say web application, you have a front-end, and there is a backend where you have written some APIs, which will interact with the particular
Grow Data Skills: you can say, MySQL application, wherever it is running, okay? Now, let's say I am a data analyst, correct? So, obviously, I'm not going to write a Python program, I'm not going to code something that, okay.
Grow Data Skills: I have now connected with this particular machine, now I can run my SQL statements. Obviously, I'm not going to do that. Being a data analyst, I'm really good at the SQL side, so I need to simply run the SQL queries. So, in that case, what
Grow Data Skills: Right? You can expect. So, for an example, when you talk about the programming languages, right, so you have a notepad as well, you have a sublime text, where you can write your entire code, okay, and save it and execute it. But what do you prefer the most? You prefer the IDE, because it's an entire development environment, which gives you the auto-completion, which gives you the syntax highlight, right, the file extension.
Grow Data Skills: everything.
Grow Data Skills: So that you can code properly, and then you can
Grow Data Skills: like, executed. If you are writing a Python program, you need a Python interpreter, and similarly, if you are just writing the Java code, so you need to convert into the bytecode and then get executed it. So, accordingly, whatever language you are using and writing the code for the same, you need the respective interpreter and compiler for the same.
Grow Data Skills: To execute your particular code.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, same thing is happening here. This is your, like, MySQL instance. So, programmatic access…
Grow Data Skills: right? We discussed about that there will be the Python Java program, and in order to connect with this database, you need another Python package, or the libraries, right? Which will have all those protocols, which will have the respective functions, methods.
Grow Data Skills: to connect from the Python code to the database, okay? But here, we will be talking about some other software application, which we call as a, probably, IDE for the databases or something. For very simple terms, this is how you can understand it, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So… For an example, this thing.
Grow Data Skills: the… DBE, where… This is another, like, application. And similar to that one, there is MySQL Workbench.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So, this is… like, I can simply call it as an ID for the SQL. This is also something I can call the same.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So these are what? DBWare, MySQL, Workbench? These are your…
Grow Data Skills: another GUI interface, right? Another kind of GUI interface which allows you to connect with the different databases.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, for an example, let's say with DB Ever, you can connect with MySQL, right? You can connect with SQL Server, right? You can connect with Oracle.
Grow Data Skills: You can connect with Postgres, Okay? And with MySQL Workbench, you can connect with various MySQL instances.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So…
Grow Data Skills: This is a GUI interface, which will simply give you an editor, right, where you'll be writing the SQL queries, and when you will execute it, that is going to get executed against the database you are connected with, right? So now let's understand that part, okay? So this is your…
Grow Data Skills: right, MySQL instance, which is running here, and it is on the cloud, okay? Now you have a DB viewer, which is, like, set up in your local, the laptop or machine you have, correct?
Grow Data Skills: So, this is your MySQL instance. So, the very first thing, what you are going to do in the DBE, where you are going to set up the connection with your MySQL.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? Because this is in your local, and this is in your cloud. So, from your local, how you are going to talk to this MySQL instance, right? So, in order to talk to this database, obviously, you need to connect with it.
Grow Data Skills: Getting the point. In order to talk to this one, you need to connect with it, correct?
Grow Data Skills: So, talking about the databases, right, what is
Grow Data Skills: bare minimum thing required to connect with the database, correct? So…
Grow Data Skills: We will list down that part.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? For the connectivity setup, you need… you need the host name, or basically, you can say IP address.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, this is very common, right? This is very common, even, let's say, today you are just typing netflix.com, right? So, this is the domain name, but, like.
Grow Data Skills: the mapping is to some specific IP address. So from your, like, Chrome client, you are simply just going to access the Netflix-related content, right, which is hosted on that specific IP address.
Grow Data Skills: So, in order to connect, or in order to set up the complete connection with this particular MySQL, you need the host name, right, or the IP address. Similarly.
Grow Data Skills: when you create the database, so let's say I am setting up the database, right? So…
Grow Data Skills: there should be someone who is there to maintain it, right? Or there should be someone who is the complete owner of it. That is what we call as an admin, right? So when I'm setting up the particular database instance, so…
Grow Data Skills: Right? There will be an admin. And…
Grow Data Skills: Even today, let's say for an example, you have a digital log applied on your doors, right? You basically put some sort of password to unlock it, and then enter it
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, in the same way, when you talk about the MySQL, so, how you are going to enter into this one, how you are going to access this particular machine. So, for that one, you need to authenticate yourself, and in order to authenticate yourself, you need a username and password.
Grow Data Skills: And when do you set up these username and password? When you basically create this particular MySQL instance, during that time itself.
Grow Data Skills: Right? You need to provide that configuration, that this will be the username, and this will be the password, right? So, once this machine is up and running, and you need to access this machine, so you need to use that specific username and password to authenticate yourself.
Grow Data Skills: So… The next thing which needed here, the username.
Grow Data Skills: And the password.
Grow Data Skills: And third important thing is the port number.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, port number… So, here…
Grow Data Skills: So now, try to understand it with respect to the client and server, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, whenever you talk about the, like.
Grow Data Skills: entire application development ecosystem. So there is always a server, and there is always one client.
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Grow Data Skills: So, server is something which is running somewhere, okay? And client is something which is allowing you to interact with that, or set up a connection with that specific server, so that you can have a interaction with it, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, when you talk about, let's say, you have a…
Grow Data Skills: web application for which you have written the entire backend, right? And…
Grow Data Skills: Again, it's a software application, so you need to run it somewhere, you need to host it somewhere, right? And that is the part, the web server, okay? So you have hosted your application here.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So now, this is the client. For an example, your Chrome browser, and when you are typing anything, as I said, some specific URL,
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so you pointed to different API endpoints.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So, this is your client, and this is your… server.
Grow Data Skills: So whenever these specific applications are running on a machine.
Grow Data Skills: Server is always simply going to listen to the incoming request, right? There is a client, obviously, which is talking to this specific server, so server is what here? Server is basically listening to all the incoming requests.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So…
Grow Data Skills: try to understand it in a way, like a mobile communication, correct? So today, let's say I have to talk to Shashang. So, Shashang might be having a mobile phone, and he has a, right, mobile number, okay? Which is…
Grow Data Skills: specific to Shashan, because he's the registered user for that one. So whenever I'm calling onto that specific number, I'm always going to get connected with the
Grow Data Skills: Shishank, right? And I will be able to talk to them. So, similarly, when you talk about the port number, right? So, port number is basically that incoming channel, right? That incoming channel for this specific
Grow Data Skills: MySQL server, wherever it is actually running, so that if there is any client who want to set up a connection, or want to talk to MySQL, they can always put a port number. So, for MySQL, default port number is 3306, right? So.
Grow Data Skills: In that case, whenever we are setting up the connection, we need to mention that specific channel as well. That on which particular incoming channel, I can connect with the MySQL and have a word with it.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So that is what your…
Grow Data Skills: port number. So with that one, we will be able to create a connection using these details, and now my DB Weaver is actually connected with this MySQL. So now, from the SQL query editor, whenever I am writing some commands, so those commands are actually going to get executed against this specific
Grow Data Skills: MySQL instance.
Grow Data Skills: Cool? So that is all about your production type of setup, right? Very basic, minimal setup, not… I didn't talk about that one, because when we will reach onto the AWS, so I will show you those things, the RDS,
Grow Data Skills: MySQL or Aurora type of setup, which you will be doing, how to configure that machine, set up username, password, everything.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, coming onto this part, how we are going to do it. So, so far we haven't reached onto the AWS. So, how you are going to practice this MySQL query, syntax, etc, step by step, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So… Here, we are going to use the MySQL Workbench, right? So, MySQL… Workbench is basically Another…
Grow Data Skills: you can say software application, which, as I said, gives you the interface to connect with the MySQL database, which is remotely present somewhere. Also, what happens
Grow Data Skills: it starts…
Grow Data Skills: Local?
Grow Data Skills: MySQL instance.
Grow Data Skills: Ken?
Grow Data Skills: Connect.
Grow Data Skills: Babe?
Grow Data Skills: remote.
Grow Data Skills: MySQL, okay? So, MySQL Workbench is that kind of, like, software application which gives you the graphical user interface to, like, write the query and also to manage the databases, to operate those type of queries.
Grow Data Skills: So, when you are setting up the MySQL workbench in your local, so during the setup part itself, right, what it will also do, if you have enabled those options, so it will also start one tiny MySQL instance in your local machine itself.
Grow Data Skills: Right? It will start one tiny MySQL instance in your local machine, although if you have any MySQL instance which is remotely presented there, so you can provide the detail for the same, and you can connect with that, correct? So, once…
Grow Data Skills: So this is what, right? We are going to simply use the MySQL workbench
Grow Data Skills: Right? For practicing all this MySQL part, as it will start the local MySQL instance.
Grow Data Skills: And when you talk about the local MySQL instance, so I hope many of you would have done it as well, if locally, if you are running some web server, right, to test some backend application code, etc. So, in your local, you basically call it as a local host. If any server, web server, or the database server is running in your local.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So…
Grow Data Skills: Here, we were talking about the host name. So, if it is present remotely, correct? If it is present remotely, it will have a specific IP address. Whatever gets generated, maybe 10, 20, comma 48, comma 96, right? This is the kind of IP address.
Grow Data Skills: But when you talk about the local.
Grow Data Skills: Any web server or any application you're starting locally.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So for all those things, right, the host will be local host, exactly, right? So… If you…
Grow Data Skills: say it like this, local host, or the IP address.
Grow Data Skills: 127001, or 0.0.0.0, right? So this is what we say, that the host will be… you can simply write local host, in this form itself, you can put this kind of IP, or this kind of IP.
Grow Data Skills: And obviously, by default, MySQL instance runs on the port number 3306, so by providing all those details, we will be able to connect with the MySQL instance.
Grow Data Skills: Also, when you are doing this setup part, MySQL workbench setup, so during the setup part itself, it will ask you to set up the password for the admin access. So, by default, the admin is going to be the root here.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, when you will be doing the setup, you will see, by default, the, like, admin name is going to be the root. So, during the setup part, it will ask you that, please create a password for this root user, correct? So, whatever
Grow Data Skills: password you will create, that is something you will be using while setting up the connection details for this local MySQL instance, for username, password, and port number. So now, I will show you that part, and from this point now, we are going to get started properly, okay? So…
Grow Data Skills: for the dedicated MySQL workbench setup, I have already given
Grow Data Skills: I'm not really sure if you checked it or not, but…
Grow Data Skills: if you are accessing it from the, web or something, so just open the course content and go into the SQL class. There you will see MySQL Workbench setup. I have provided two dedicated YouTube video links, which are very latest, one for
Grow Data Skills: MySQL work event set up in the Mac, and another for MySQL Workbench setup in the Windows, right? So…
Grow Data Skills: 30-minute long videos, and every single step has been explained precisely, that how you are going to set up the MySQL workbench, and
Grow Data Skills: creating the connection, right? But I'm going to show you those steps, at least here.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, how do you, going to… how are you going to set up the MySQL workbench, let's say, in the, MacBook? So, simply type this thing, MySQL Workbench.
Grow Data Skills: Set up… Mac.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, this is the, you can say, main…
Grow Data Skills: URL you need to follow, right? The dev.mysql.com, Correct?
Grow Data Skills: And, here, these steps are given, that is fine, yeah.
Grow Data Skills: So, you will be redirected on this page, or maybe directly you will be redirected on this downloads page. Because, as I said, MySQL Workbench is what? It is a proper software application which you need to first download in your system, and then you need to install it properly, the way you, like, do other type of setups as well.
Grow Data Skills: So, here, if I open this one, Workbench.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So…
Grow Data Skills: Similarly, the way I have typed MySQL workbench setup for Mac, you can also type the MySQL workbench setup for Windows. It will directly take you to this kind of download page, where
Grow Data Skills: right, you can see, if I want it for the macOS, I can select the respective operating system. So, macOS is already set up. Let's say you are doing it for the Windows. So, for the macOS, this .dmg file would get downloaded, right? So, download this one itself.
Grow Data Skills: right, the first one, you can simply download it, and once that .dmg file is downloaded, just double-click on it, and it will start
Grow Data Skills: like… It will start popping up those screens where
Grow Data Skills: you will see the steps for the installation. Just do the next, set up the path, okay? And the admin name will be root, and that time it will ask you to provide the password, and…
Grow Data Skills: when you are doing the setup itself, it will give you the pop-up that when you are setting up the MySQL workbench.
Grow Data Skills: Right? What all services you want to initiate. So make sure that MySQL Server Service, you definitely check that part, else it will not initiate the local MySQL instance setup. And these steps, as I said, it is already…
Grow Data Skills: like, covered in that specific setup video, which I have already provided the link for.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? And similarly, if you open this Microsoft Windows, this part, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, this kind of… are…
Grow Data Skills: right, MSI installer file will get downloaded, right? And then simply you can double-click on that one, and it will run the installer, where it will ask you to proceed with the different steps to complete the setup, right? So, after today's session, this will be also your task, right, to do the setup and whatever queries, right.
Grow Data Skills: we are going to run today, creating the database, creating the tables. You need to execute them, okay?
Grow Data Skills: And, by any chance you face any type of difficulty related to the setup, right? So, obviously, you can discuss it with me, you can get connected with me in the Discord, right?
Grow Data Skills: And I hope you have the access for the Discord. If not, again, don't worry, don't get impatient. After today's session, just watch that induction session, or open your course content.
Grow Data Skills: I have given the Discord a link. Discord is just like Slack or Microsoft Teams, where you'll be having an offline doubt discussion with me. Whenever you come up with any technical doubts, just post it there, or…
Grow Data Skills: like, connect with me in a personal DM, and I will assist you for all other things, okay? Whenever you come up with any technical type of issues, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, don't worry about these things. I mean, if you have free time, you want to follow it right now, so just open it in your laptop or desktop, and you start doing it in parallel, not a problem. If not, after this session, you can do that. And if you run with any challenge.
Grow Data Skills: Feel free to reach out on the Discord, and I will help you with the setup part. And setup-related guide, as I said, I have already provided there the YouTube video links, they are already in place. Dedicatedly, you can follow them for Windows or Mac, and easily you will be able to set it up. Very easy steps.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So now, once… after doing this part, your setup part is done, right? So how you are going to access it? The… this part, let's say.
Grow Data Skills: the MySQL workbench. So, I'm using the Mac machine, so I'm now going to open the workbench. So, I'm going to type this thing, let's say MySQL Workbench.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So, this is how it is going to look like.
Grow Data Skills: So, once you will open the MySQL Workbench for the very first time after completing the full installation, this is how it will look like, right? So, here you can see, Workbench is an official GUI tool for the MySQL.
Grow Data Skills: It allows you to design, create, browse your database, right, and manipulate, etc, etc. And this is the part I was talking about that I have created the
Grow Data Skills: connections, correct? So, just forget about these things as of now. So, just look at this part, right? Look at this part. So, sometime back, right, when I was taking the GCP data engineering, I created one MySQL instance on the GCP, correct? And after that, what I did, I simply
Grow Data Skills: created one MySQL instance there, so I wanted to run some queries on top of it. So, what I had to do, I simply had to come to this MySQL workbench, and I had to create a new connection there, correct? So, how you can create and set up a new connection?
Grow Data Skills: So, you can see this plus icon here, MySQL connection, this plus icon, just click on that.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So once you click on this, Okay, so…
Grow Data Skills: Cool. So this is the part you can see here, the connection name.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So here, let's say, MySQL GCP…
Grow Data Skills: connection, okay? So, MySQL GCP connection, now this is the host name. See? This is what I was talking about, that
Grow Data Skills: let's say…
Grow Data Skills: So, when you will initiate the MySQL workbench, it will start one local MySQL instance, as I said, okay? So, to access your local MySQL instance, the IP address, the host name will be localhost. So, either you can type this thing here, like the local host.
Grow Data Skills: Or you can type 127.0.0.1, or you can also type 0.0.0.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? But when you talk about the MySQL instance remotely on a cloud, so it will have a dedicated IP address. So maybe, let's say, it was 1098, 20, and 45. So I have given this host name. Now, by default, on which port MySQL instance runs, it runs on 3306.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Cool, we are good as of now. Now, coming to the username and password, correct? So when…
Grow Data Skills: Let's say there was a…
Grow Data Skills: database admin, right? Or there was a dedicated DevOps team, they created one database instance, and they are the admin of it. So, they have the root access. Now.
Grow Data Skills: I…
Grow Data Skills: like, I'm Sashang Mishra, and what I want to do, I am a data engineer, and I need the access for that specific database, so that I can connect with it, and I can do my stuff.
Grow Data Skills: So, what I will do, I will raise a request to that DBA, right, the database admin, or I will raise the request to the DevOps team that, hey, you have created a new MySQL instance, I need access for it. So now what that admin team will do, they will
Grow Data Skills: basically log in into this MySQL instance, and will access the system tables of the MySQL instance which we have initiated, and they will create a new user.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, very similar, right? So, for an example, you have created one mobile application, correct? So, you are the owner of it, so obviously you have access of it. Now you want to give Shashank or Rahul to the access for this application, so what you will do?
Grow Data Skills: You will create one username and password, and you will pass them, right? That, hey, Shashang, use this username and password to log in and access. So, same thing, admin will be doing it. He will be creating one new user and password.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, how that is going to be done?
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so… This is the part.
Grow Data Skills: So, let's say the username was Shashank219, right? That is the username admin has created. Now, for the password part, I mean, this is how it looks like in Mac.
Grow Data Skills: And maybe if you are opening it in the Windows, it might give you another box itself to store the password. So here, once you click on the store in keychain, what it will ask, provide the password for this username. So whatever password your admin has shared with you, you just need to put it here.
Grow Data Skills: But here, you are doing the entire local setup, so you are the admin.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So you are the admin, so when you are setting this up, so what you can say, local.
Grow Data Skills: MySQL.
Grow Data Skills: connection, okay? So, 1270.1, and I… so when, as I said, when you will be installing and setting up the MySQL workbench.
Grow Data Skills: So, by default, you are the admin, and the username for the admin is this one.
Grow Data Skills: Username for the admin is root, right? And the password?
Grow Data Skills: right, whatever is the password, you can simply type here. So, this password, as I said, during the installation time, it will ask you that, hey, which password you want to give for the
Grow Data Skills: like admin user, which is rude. So whatever password you provide at that time, make sure to note it down somewhere, so that you don't forget it. Else, sometimes it becomes a little bit challenging to, just…
Grow Data Skills: like…
Grow Data Skills: reset that, right? You will have to follow a few good number of steps to do that, so if you don't want to go into that challenge, it's better that you simply note it down that particular password and put it somewhere so that you can later on log in.
Grow Data Skills: So, let me put my password here.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, after putting that password detail, what I did, I clicked on the test connection. So, once I did the test connection, so you can see, successfully made the MySQL connection. So, now this IDE, right, this workbench.
Grow Data Skills: Wherever my local MySQL instance was running it, it has made a successful connection with it. So I'll just click on OK, and we'll click on this OK as well.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So now you can see this new connection is created. So now, after that, if I will double-click on it.
Grow Data Skills: You can see?
Grow Data Skills: This is how it will look like, and this is actually your
Grow Data Skills: editor I was talking about. So, for your programming languages, let's say you are using the,
Grow Data Skills: you are using the Visual Studio Code, PyCharm, or IntelliJ. So, similarly, you see a code editor there, where you write something something. Now, here, this is a graphical user interface, where you are seeing this query
Grow Data Skills: Editor, where you will be writing the queries, and now, whatever database you are connected with, this query is going to get executed against that database itself.
Grow Data Skills: Right? And you will be able to see that thing entirely. So, currently, you can see
Grow Data Skills: right, on the left-hand side. If you look at this left-hand side, there is one cis. So, cis is what? Right? This is our…
Grow Data Skills: database. We have already, like.
Grow Data Skills: this gets created when you are setting up the MySQL workbench, so this gets already created there, and in this one, right, MySQL basically
Grow Data Skills: keeps all the system-related tables, which is not exposed to the user, and user cannot manipulate it, right? Internally, it will be managed by MySQL application itself. For an example.
Grow Data Skills: Admin has created a new user, so keeping the username and password into the system table. When you are creating the table, so storing the create table command. When you are running various queries and your query is failing, so storing them in the error table, right, so that you can debug that what kind of error has happened with particular query you are running.
Grow Data Skills: So… if I take you to this one again, right, this particular slide, and explain you this part.
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Grow Data Skills: So, this was your MySQL.
Grow Data Skills: This was your MySQL, and…
Grow Data Skills: This is your RDBMS.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? Now, inside this one, what you will be doing, you can create multiple databases.
Grow Data Skills: So, let's say this is… DB1.
Grow Data Skills: DB2, and within each database, you can create multiple tables, right? Table 1, Table 2… Table 3.
Grow Data Skills: Maybe table 4… Table 5, and table…
Grow Data Skills: 6. So, what this DB1 and DB2 means, so DB1, DB2 means here, these are your logical containers.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Logical containers or logical namespace within an RDBMS, right? So, logical namespace within an RDBMS, and inside these namespaces or containers, you will be creating various tables.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So when I am saying this thing, right, that…
Grow Data Skills: this part. That you are able to see this thing, okay? That cis.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, if I open it, sysconfig, right, this is the kind of system table, which is already created there, because this is the application in itself, okay? This is the application in itself. So…
Grow Data Skills: in order to maintain the metadata-related information, it has already created one database for itself. So, if I take you to this statement.
Grow Data Skills: So… For this particular part, right?
Grow Data Skills: So I'm talking with respect to the MySQL workbench.
Grow Data Skills: So, this is the Sys database.
Grow Data Skills: This is a system database, by default created. We have not created it.
Grow Data Skills: Now, what we will start doing, we will start running the SQL queries to create these database and the tables on our own. So the only thing which you can see
Grow Data Skills: Right now is this particular system database, which is the default one created by the particular workbench itself to maintain the metadata.
Grow Data Skills: Now, these databases we can create, then we can create the table inside it, and I will
Grow Data Skills: keep on talking about the various categories of the SQL commands as well, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, I think it's a time for a break now. Okay, so let's take a 5-minute of water break, and we will meet around 10.27.
Grow Data Skills: And then, from there, we will continue with the, like, SQL queries part. We will create the database, create the table inside it, and the actual thing, the various parts we were doing, okay? So we'll do that in that way.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, it's good you guys are raising the hands, but I will take the doubts at the end, as I mentioned, Srijit and other folks. So, for the doubt part, we will be doing it at the end, okay? Don't worry about it, your doubts will be picked.
Grow Data Skills: Cool, alright.
Grow Data Skills: Cool, so let's take a short break, and let's meet around 10.27, right? Okay.
Grow Data Skills: Alright, let's get started.
Grow Data Skills: So, Gotham, yes, there was no audio, because I already mentioned there was a 5 minute of water break.
Grow Data Skills: Cool, let's get started now.
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Grow Data Skills: Cool, so this is the workbench, as I mentioned, so now let's get started, and let's…
Grow Data Skills: Work on these things, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, for an example, that,
Grow Data Skills: So, first thing, as I mentioned, right?
Grow Data Skills: that, what we want to do, okay? And there are a few other internally created databases which are not visible to us, as I said, right? Because these are internally created by this. So the very first command which I'm going to show, let's say there is a already running MySQL database, and your
Grow Data Skills: a team lead has simply given you the access of that, okay? He has given you the access of that, and now…
Grow Data Skills: what you simply want to do, right? That… how you are going to check how many databases are already created there. As I mentioned, the database is simply going to be the logical namespace there. Inside that, you'll be creating multiple tables, right? So…
Grow Data Skills: how you are going to see the databases which are already presented there. So, the very first command which we are going to get started with, okay, so command to…
Grow Data Skills: List down databases.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? And on the MySQL Workbench editor, right, when you are… or, first thing I forgot to tell you, that how do you open a new, let's say, SQL editor, right? So, on the very left-hand side, you can see, right, this is a plus icon, create a new SQL, right? So, if you just click on it, right, you will see that it will open up a
Grow Data Skills: blank, like, SQL file, which you can simply use and start writing the queries. And since whatever database you are connected with, you will be simply able to
Grow Data Skills: run the queries against that, okay? So, command to list down the databases. So…
Grow Data Skills: the command is very simple, which is show databases whenever you are logging onto this one, right? So, if you… now, let's say this is the particular… I'm just talking with respect to MySQL workbench, right? This is the particular SQL command you have written, right? And…
Grow Data Skills: After that, you simply just want to execute this one. So how you are going to do it? Just simply select this thing, and there is the one, you can see the thunder icon, right? So just, just simply click on that one, and here you can see it has
Grow Data Skills: executed this show databases command, right? So now, in the output, I hope you are able to see there is an output which is listing down the databases which are already created. So one database named as information schema, MySQL, Performance Schema, and sys.
Grow Data Skills: So, these are the default databases already created. As I told you, right, some of the databases will not be exposed to the user itself, because it is something maintained and accessed by the particular application itself, the workbench application, right?
Grow Data Skills: So, this is how it is, and…
Grow Data Skills: This is very simple, right? And step by step, now we'll be doing…
Grow Data Skills: the practical part of it, right? Starting with the create table, and step by step, you will see each and everything. And we will be touching on each and everything. So at any point, don't get impatient that.
Grow Data Skills: When that particular topic is going to come, when that particular topic is going to come, for example, we'll deep dive into the integrity constraints, primary key, foreign key, joins, subqueries, group by, case when, conditional aggregate, windows, everything, step by step, we will reach onto those things, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, this is the command, as I said, you executed, just to list down the existing databases, okay? Now, how you can simply create a new database, right? The…
Grow Data Skills: like, I created that, representation where I showed you that databases are what? They are basically the container or the logical representation there, okay? So, how you are going to create a fresh database.
Grow Data Skills: And within that, how you are going to create new tables, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, let's look at that part.
Grow Data Skills: So, in order to create the database, How… to create… database, okay? So… Command is very simple.
Grow Data Skills: Create…
Grow Data Skills: database, right? These are the result keywords, right? Create, database, and after that, you need to give a database name.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So…
Grow Data Skills: Data Engineer DB, okay? So now, if I just select this thing, and click on this thunder icon, correct? So…
Grow Data Skills: This got executed, and now, if you just come up here and just refresh, you can see, right, this refresh icon is here.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So once you just simply click on this refresh, now you can see this Data Engineering DB. This is a new database we have created, and it is showing up here on this left-hand side.
Grow Data Skills: And this is the actual advantage of using the GUI, like the Workbench DB Weaver, because
Grow Data Skills: when you are directly logging onto the machine and doing everything from the command line. So, a lot of times, you have to see and check everything by executing the commands. But, on the GUI, all these things are
Grow Data Skills: already reflecting, and as a user, it becomes easier to navigate and see what is already presented there, and how you can look at it. So, now if you just click on this expand icon, so you can see various things here. One is the tables.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, when we will be creating the tables, that will actually come up here, and then we will create the views, right? So, they will come up here, and if we are creating any stored procedure, they will reflect here, and if we are creating any customized function… So, in the beginning, I mentioned
Grow Data Skills: There are a few inbuilt functions, which you can always use, like the mathematical sum, min, max, average.
Grow Data Skills: and other date-related functions, etc. Right? But if you are creating your own function, so they will simply reflect here.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, this is how we created a new database.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? I will create one more database for an example.
Grow Data Skills: Just this thing.
Grow Data Skills: Create… database.
Grow Data Skills: Test.
Grow Data Skills: leaving.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so let's just execute it.
Grow Data Skills: So, I did that, and now if I again refresh it here, so you will see that TestDB has also come up here, okay? So, why I created another database? So, for an example, there is a database which is already created, right? And you just simply want to delete it.
Grow Data Skills: Completely, right? You simply want to delete it completely. The database part I'm talking about, so how you can delete any existing database, right?
Grow Data Skills: How to delete?
Grow Data Skills: Existing.
Grow Data Skills: database. So, for that one, the command is very simple.
Grow Data Skills: drop?
Grow Data Skills: database.
Grow Data Skills: Right? And after that, you simply need to mention what is that particular database, right? So just simply select that thing, right? So drop database means we simply want to drop this particular database entirely. We simply want to remove that, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So let's just…
Grow Data Skills: Execute it, okay? And now, on the left-hand side, you can see that database has already vanished.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, create database, simple command, and if you already have a database, and no matter the tables are present inside that, or not.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, drop database. So, that is why drop, delete-related commands are very, very crucial. So, when you are actually working on a production grade of system, so admin definitely does not give you these kind of accesses a lot, right?
Grow Data Skills: So, the admin is simply going to give you the access
Grow Data Skills: For the, maybe, create, or the select, or the alter, etc, but drop or delete.
Grow Data Skills: right, by mistake, even if you run it, this is like a nightmare, okay? So, you won't be having these kind of accesses.
Grow Data Skills: Right? At all on the production kind of the databases, until unless you are the admin of it.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, drop database.
Grow Data Skills: And, right, there is a phrase as well, or simple saying, I guess, in the software engineering world itself, that
Grow Data Skills: When you are working with the databases in production, just forget there is anything related to drop and delete, right? Just remember there is only select, alter, etc, but nothing related to delete and drop.
Grow Data Skills: Cool.
Grow Data Skills: So…
Grow Data Skills: Now, before actually getting into the main command, so we saw this thing that, okay, we have a database, we created it, we saw how to delete the database as well. So before starting the, like, first create table command, etc, right, what we need to understand
Grow Data Skills: So, when we talk about the SQL, right, entirely, so…
Grow Data Skills: when we talk about the SQL entirely, it is basically divided into the 4 to 5 categories, primarily 4 categories, right, but 5 as well. So, what categories? Category means
Grow Data Skills: how individual SQL command is actually divided into the different categories here. So, for an example, there are… primarily, I'm going to talk about four categories.
Grow Data Skills: DDL, DML.
Grow Data Skills: And, DCL… Right, data definition.
Grow Data Skills: Data definition.
Grow Data Skills: Shouldn't… Language… The full form of it, data manipulation.
Grow Data Skills: Data control… Okay, and then coming on to the last one, which is our DQL.
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Grow Data Skills: DQL, data query language.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so I was talking about primarily four, there are 5 as well, which are more related to the transactional control, etc, but for the SQL, we'll keep our focus majorly on these 4 categories. So, now, when I will keep on writing various SQL commands.
Grow Data Skills: I will keep on describing what individual category means, and this particular command in which category it is going to fall in, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, what DDL eventually means, so DDL, the full form is Data Definition Language.
Grow Data Skills: And what does it actually mean here? That any SQL query or command you are writing, which will have a direct impact on the table structure, right? Or the blueprint I was talking about, okay? So that is going to fall under the DDL category.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Now, what is the DML? So, DML means those kind of SQL commands
Grow Data Skills: Right? Which you are going to use to manipulate the data which is stored in the database. Like, data manipulation is, you already have some data in the table, and you are deleting one specific record. So you are manipulating it. You are updating it, you are inserting a new record, right? So these are what… this is…
Grow Data Skills: what is related to the DML, data manipulation?
Grow Data Skills: Right? Similarly, the DCL part, data control language, okay? So, what does it mean? So, for an example, when…
Grow Data Skills: So, controlling means when you are creating the tables, you have the data, and…
Grow Data Skills: you want to take care of the access part, right? Controlling the access for the user. So, whatever command, basically, you use for that thing, that falls under the data control language. Means, granting the access, so two examples for that one. So…
Grow Data Skills: There are two SQL commands as well, grant and revoke. So, grant command you basically use to grant certain permissions of running few specific SQL commands.
Grow Data Skills: to a specific user or user group, okay? For an example, the scenario I was explaining, that there is a DevOps team who has set up one MySQL instance on the cloud, and now I am the data engineer hired in that team, and I need to work on that specific
Grow Data Skills: You can say, data bills, correct? So…
Grow Data Skills: Now, that admin will create a username and password, and for that specific user, I am a very new team member, so that admin might want to simply allow me the read-related permissions, okay? That admin, right? He simply want to…
Grow Data Skills: Like, he simply want to allow me the read-related permission. So, that is going to be the…
Grow Data Skills: You can say, granting the select permission, not the delete, right, or the drop, or truncate, but only the select command.
Grow Data Skills: So, what he will be doing, grant, select on this particular table or database to use a session. Similarly, if I want to take that permission, so admin, earlier he gave me the delete-related permission, now he want to revoke it, right? So, he can simply run the revoke command.
Grow Data Skills: Similarly, data query language. So, in this one, you will have this select statement. Okay? So, select statement means
Grow Data Skills: querying a particular table, right? So, whatever command or keyword you are going to use for that thing falls under the DQL, so select falls under this one.
Grow Data Skills: And similarly, create…
Grow Data Skills: drop, right? These are something, and alter… these will fall under the data definition language, because these commands will directly have an impact on the table structure or the blueprint you have created. DML part I talked about, let's say insert…
Grow Data Skills: Right? Update… Delete, right? So these are simply going to be the DML.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, as soon as we will be practicing various commands, right? So…
Grow Data Skills: I will keep on pointing out which particular category I'm talking about. So now, if you talk about, let's say, joins, group by, etc, they are simply the operations, right? They are not any specific
Grow Data Skills: SQL commands, right, which will fall under categories, right? They are the operations, so don't get confused that
Grow Data Skills: when we talk about these four categories, so joins, group by window function will be also falling in some categories. They are simply the operations.
Grow Data Skills: But, apart from that, related to your tables, related to the data manipulation, related to the access, whatever commands you'll be using, they will have a specific category, like DDL, DML, DCL, and DQL.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so let's get started now. So we created a database, we also looked at how to delete a particular database.
Grow Data Skills: Correct, so let me… Put a comment here.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So…
Grow Data Skills: what we are going to do that, let's say I have created this database, right? Now what I want to do, I want to simply create one table inside this database. So what do I need to do here?
Grow Data Skills: So, first, you created a database, and after that, you need to get inside this database, okay? So, in order to get inside this particular database, what we are going to do, we are going to simply execute, use.
Grow Data Skills: This is the keyword, and after that, you simply need to mention the particular database name.
Grow Data Skills: So, when you write this thing, use this database name, means now.
Grow Data Skills: From the reference point of view, you are completely, entirely inside this logical database you have created. So, now, after doing this, whatever table you will be creating, you can simply mention the table name, and start doing it.
Grow Data Skills: So, just run this part. Now you can see, right, on the left-hand side, you actually saw some changes reflecting. When you executed this thing, automatically it has got highlighted in the bold color, and
Grow Data Skills: Right? Automatically, it expanded it, right? So, which says, from the GUI perspective, if this is dark, highlighted, means currently you are inside this database.
Grow Data Skills: So, whatever select command, create table, or anything you are going to execute it, right? So, that will get executed inside it.
Grow Data Skills: For an example, we had this particular database as well.
Grow Data Skills: Right? And… Currently, I am not inside any specific database, right?
Grow Data Skills: And there is one table which is already present inside this database, which is, let's say, dummy table. And I want to access that particular table, so…
Grow Data Skills: when…
Grow Data Skills: you have not stepped into any specific database, and you want to access certain tables of that database, so whenever you will be writing this DQL command, right, this select command.
Grow Data Skills: So there, you always need to call your table with databaseename.table name.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, once we will reach onto the select command, I will talk about it. So, db name, dot…
Grow Data Skills: table name, right? So this is…
Grow Data Skills: the way you basically write the table names if you have not stepped into any specific database, and you just want to access the tables of it, right? So, database name and the table name.
Grow Data Skills: Correct?
Grow Data Skills: Cool.
Grow Data Skills: So now…
Grow Data Skills: what we are going to do, once we are inside this database, we are going to create our first table, right? A very simple table with just two columns, right? And we'll try to see, how does it look like.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: Not maybe 2 columns, but four columns. So what is the command to create a table? Okay? So, create…
Grow Data Skills: table… Okay, and after that, table name.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so create, table, employees, Okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, create is a keyword, table is a keyword, and after that, you are giving a table name. So, when we basically write this create table command, okay, so we can do one more thing here, right? So, we only want this table to get created in a situation
Grow Data Skills: When it does not exist.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Because, let's say there is a table which is already created, and you are simply running this command again, it might fail with the error response, that table already exists.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, in order to prevent that scenario, how you are going to do that? Simply create table, and after that, you can put a statement like, if
Grow Data Skills: not exists.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So what does it mean? Create a table if that particular table does not exist. And what will be the name of that table? It will be employees.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, after that, what you simply need to do.
Grow Data Skills: Right? You need to define the structure of the table, which we saw, there was an employee table, so when we say the structure of a table, what does it mean? How many columns are going to be there, and what will be the data type of each column?
Grow Data Skills: So, again, understand it from the programming perspective. Let's say you have written a Java code, and
Grow Data Skills: the Java code you have written, basically, to… Add two integer numbers, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, in that case, what actually happens, from the user, what you are expecting? You are expecting two integer numbers, right? And when you are writing the Java code, so what you will be doing, you will define two variables, right, which will accept those two input
Grow Data Skills: values from the user. User is providing the integer value, so in your Java code, the two variables you are going to define, those has to be of integer type.
Grow Data Skills: So that those variables can hold the integer value.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? And same thing applies on the…
Grow Data Skills: this database itself, right? When you are creating the blueprint or the structure of the tables, so what you are eventually doing, you are defining how many columns are going to be there, and what will be the data type of each column.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Whether… so, imagine, when you talk about the name column. So, name is what? Name is basically a string type of column. It will always hold the string type of data, correct? When you talk about the
Grow Data Skills: let's say joining date, right? So, joining date is basically of the data data type. It will always have the date value, like the YYYMMDD format, right?
Grow Data Skills: And when you talk about the, let's say, salary part, so that is something which could be of the long integer, right? So, generally, you don't give salaries in the fractional, right? Your salary is 100 rupees, 50 pesa, right? Nothing like that, but simply a very…
Grow Data Skills: Like, integer number. Long integer it could be, but an integer. So, salary, as I said, the integer number.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So that is how it is going to be.
Grow Data Skills: Sorry. Okay? So, here, how we are now going to define the blueprint of it, or the table structure.
Grow Data Skills: So, here, just open one small parenthesis and also close it. Now, inside these parentheses, you basically keep on writing about the column name and respective data types, column names and the respective data types.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, that is what I'm going to do now. So, first column is the ID, right? ID means the employee ID, and I want to keep the data type of it as integer.
Grow Data Skills: Now, your question will be, Shishank, there, how many data types are there? How can I memorize that? Again, as I said, there is nothing related to the memorization part here.
Grow Data Skills: Basic types you already know, like the string, integer, float, date, etc. But whenever you have, like, to work with the complicated data types, or you need to always refer something, my best practice is to always look at the official documentation page, because it always have
Grow Data Skills: all the informations. Even I don't remember all the data types which are present in the MySQL, okay? As simple as that. So, you can simply access that thing. So, here, if you come up…
Grow Data Skills: MySQL data types.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So here, this is the reference manual for the data types.
Grow Data Skills: And here, you can simply start
Grow Data Skills: Looking at it, like, what are the different numeric data types, Okay?
Grow Data Skills: And, here, the… this one, the integer type, right? So, all the details are given that how do you actually write it?
Grow Data Skills: the proper syntax of it, and how many storage bytes they will acquire in the memory. Similarly, the decimal type, float type, okay?
Grow Data Skills: And, here, if you look at the string-related data type, Correct?
Grow Data Skills: So, string data type, car, var care, right? All these things. So, the documentation is already given for it. So, as I said, I personally don't remember
Grow Data Skills: All and each and every data type, but the most common one used, most of the people already know that, but if you have any complicated one to use, you can always refer the documentation page for the same.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So here, ID, I'm keeping as an integer type, okay? So, this is how you provide the column name, and just after that, you mention its data type. And if there are new columns you need to add, then just put a comma, and do the same for the other columns, right?
Grow Data Skills: And after creating the table, we will discuss about it, that how…
Grow Data Skills: Like, it is going to work, and what kind of storage, etc, it is going to occupy.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, if you come up here… One thing, the date…
Grow Data Skills: Date parameters are here.
Grow Data Skills: Mmm… yeah.
Grow Data Skills: So, we'll be having date-related functions as well. We're just checking one thing…
Grow Data Skills: Anyways, that is not given here.
Grow Data Skills: Cool. So, ID, and now talking about the employee name, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So here, you can say, employee.
Grow Data Skills: name, and this employee name is going to be of a string type, as I said. So, now, when you talk about the MySQL, in order to define any column which is going to store the data in the alphabetical, form, okay? So, instead of
Grow Data Skills: typical string…
Grow Data Skills: word, we simply use the var-kar, right? The car or varkar. So, there are two different types in that one itself, car and workar. So, car…
Grow Data Skills: Right? It basically covers a very limited range of the alphabets, but when you talk about those kind of columns, which might have a special character, unified characters as well, so you need to go for a different, longer range, right, which… that kind of data type, which can support those kind of
Grow Data Skills: Sky values as well. So for that one, we have a var car.
Grow Data Skills: So, we put it like this, var care, and in the brackets, we also mention the length, correct? So, imagine we are setting up the database.
Grow Data Skills: Because everything is related to the memory part as well, right? So…
Grow Data Skills: It's not like there is a string column.
Grow Data Skills: and the maximum characters in that string column can come up to 5 characters, but when you created this particular column, you mentioned var 100.
Grow Data Skills: So what you are doing, you are wasting the memory, right? I will tell you, after creating this table structure, I will also tell you how data is going to get stored in the memory of the database, right? So that you can understand
Grow Data Skills: that why everything matters here, with respect to the memory and storage part as well, correct? So, ID, integer type, employee name, worker, let's say.
Grow Data Skills: 10, right? I have kept it like this.
Grow Data Skills: And the third column, salary.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Let's say this is also, I have kept it as an integer.
Grow Data Skills: And now, the last column, let's say, hiring date.
Grow Data Skills: Which is of data data type. So this is a very simple example of the create table I have taken. There is nothing related to integrity constraints, no default values, etc, because we will go on to that one step by step, right? But currently, we are looking at a very simple createTable command.
Grow Data Skills: And then after that, we will see how does it work.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, this is what we have done, and now if you just select it, and you just run this part.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so this got executed, now if you expand it, and just refresh this particular thing one more time.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So once I refresh it, now you can see table has been expanded, and I am able to see the employees table.
Grow Data Skills: And if I expand it… So, why this GUI is becoming more helpful? So, here you are able to see all the columns which are present here. And if you have created the index, so in the last session, we will talk about the indexes as well, right? What index means, how do we create a index on the table?
Grow Data Skills: And if there is a particular foreign key kind of constraint you have created, and for any type of stored procedure, if you have created any triggers as well. So, respectively, in these sections, they will come up here, okay? But currently, this is a very simple and plain table. We have not done anything else here.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, now, once we did this thing, so…
Grow Data Skills: Right? When we talk about the RDB MS, and specifically these MySQL, Postgres, Oracle, MSSQL servers.
Grow Data Skills: Right? They actually store the data in the
Grow Data Skills: like, row format, right? So, after the SQL sessions, when we will move on to the NoSQL databases, there, as I said, we will be talking about the, different type of the databases as well, NoSQL databases.
Grow Data Skills: And among that, there will be a columnar database, document-based database, key-value pair-based database, graph-based databases, so multiple NoSQL databases. But when you talk about the typical RDB MS,
Grow Data Skills: They actually store the data in the raw form. So what actually it means, right, is storing the data in the raw format. So I'll quickly explain it so that anyone who does not have a clarity from the memory storage perspective, you have that understanding as well.
Grow Data Skills: So…
Grow Data Skills: Row-based storage.
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Grow Data Skills: So, let's say I have created this thing.
Grow Data Skills: Create… table…
Grow Data Skills: Create, table, users, And here, let's see…
Grow Data Skills: ID equals to of integer type.
Grow Data Skills: And uname means username of… VAR car 10.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, if you have to imagine how this blank table will look like, currently this blank table in the database will simply look like this, because it does not have any sort of row as of now, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So here, this is your ID column, and this is your uname column.
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Grow Data Skills: So, let's go into the basics of the,
Grow Data Skills: Computer science, okay? And even the programming languages, etc. I am hoping that when you have gone through with these
Grow Data Skills: Programming language type of, programming language type of concepts, right?
Grow Data Skills: So, you must have understood, with respect to the storage point of view of the different data types, right? That when you are actually defining a particular variable to be of integer type, to be of
Grow Data Skills: float type to be of long integer type, then in the memory, what amount of space they are going to occupy, okay? So.
Grow Data Skills: tell me, for integer, how much it is going to be, if I have declared any variable, so generally, how much memory bytes integer is going to occupy in the memory.
Grow Data Skills: How many bytes of space it will occupy.
Grow Data Skills: It will be 4 bytes. Correct.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, 4 bytes of…
Grow Data Skills: Or you can say, yeah, 4 bytes, correct? Now, talking about the var car, so, if I talk about the car character only, so, in general.
Grow Data Skills: Care how much memory bytes it is going to occupy.
Grow Data Skills: It is going to be 1 byte, absolutely, okay? So, 1 byte.
Grow Data Skills: So here, if I'm talking about var care at 10, correct? If I'm talking about var care at 10, so how much, right, how much memory bytes it is going to occupy?
Grow Data Skills: Right? How much it is going to be? Because var care of length, 10.
Grow Data Skills: Not depends on the data, it depends, because this one, like, car, worker, like, 1 byte here, the length is going to be the 10 here.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Because one…
Grow Data Skills: CAR is taking one byte, but if we are creating a particular, column, right, where var care of length 10, so how much it is going to occupy, it is going to occupy 10 bytes, correct?
Grow Data Skills: Super 10.
Grow Data Skills: Cool.
Grow Data Skills: So now… ID, comma, username, this is your columns, column names, right?
Grow Data Skills: And your data will be in the row format. So, for an example, if I am…
Grow Data Skills: There is a backend application… What it has done, for ID, it has this value, 100, and for username.
Grow Data Skills: It has value, this thing.
Grow Data Skills: Amit.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So… 100, Amit?
Grow Data Skills: Cool, so this is how it is going to be.
Grow Data Skills: So, this is going to be the data for row 1, which you are going to add. So, how your row 1 will look like? Your row 1 will look like this. It will have this value.
Grow Data Skills: 100, and Amit.
Grow Data Skills: So now, if I talk about row 1, so when I'm storing this data, or I'm inserting this data into this database, how much
Grow Data Skills: Memory this row 1 is going to occupy in the database.
Grow Data Skills: How much memory this row 1 is going to occupy in the database?
Grow Data Skills: So, someone is saying 8 byte, someone is saying 14 byte.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, which answer is correct?
Grow Data Skills: 14 or 8.
Grow Data Skills: So, see, what I explained here, right, when you are talking about the row here, correct?
Grow Data Skills: So, with respect to the occupy, right, when you are occupying it, so, see, when you are creating a row, right, it is going to follow this structure.
Grow Data Skills: Right? And based on this structure, your ID is of 4 byte, and your username is of 10 bytes.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, in this case, what is going to happen, right, overall, for every row which you are going to get create, right.
Grow Data Skills: Entire 14 bytes will be allocated.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Because 4 bytes here, and 10 bytes for workar. So, entirely, 14 bytes for…
Grow Data Skills: one specific row, whenever you will try to insert it, right? So, that is how it is going to happen. Because for this integer type, okay, if you store 1, if you store 100, or if you store 1 lakh, right, it is going to occupy how much?
Grow Data Skills: 4 bytes. Similarly, when you talk about this second column, which is of what? Which is of the var length 10. So, no matter if you are storing 1 character, 2 characters, 5 characters, or at max 10 characters, how much memory it is going to
Grow Data Skills: Put here with respect to this row 1.
Grow Data Skills: Sorry. All the… 10 bytes. So that is why Total?
Grow Data Skills: 14 bytes, correct? So now what I actually meant, that the data is stores in the row format. So data stores in the row format, right? What does it mean?
Grow Data Skills: that… It is actually…
Grow Data Skills: when you are storing the data, so the rows are actually getting created in the contiguous memory locations, right? So, I'll just come here, and we'll explain it
Grow Data Skills: A little bit more.
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Grow Data Skills: So… Imagine this is the… area. This is the memory area.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: No… This is your memory area, and if I divide it this way…
Grow Data Skills: 3, 4, 5… 6… 7, 8, 9, 10, 11… 12.
Grow Data Skills: Maybe in between 13, 14.
Grow Data Skills: 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.
Grow Data Skills: 13, 14, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So this is your entire memory area, and when you talk about the, right.
Grow Data Skills: So, when you actually talk about the, memory blocks, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, memory blocks here, right? So, in this case, what is going to happen, right? So, in this case.
Grow Data Skills: when you actually talk about the memory blocks, it has the memory address, right? It has the memory addresses, which is of a hexadecimal, sorry, which is of the hex representations, okay? But here, I will make it very simple for you.
Grow Data Skills: tonight.
Grow Data Skills: Just a second…
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So… Let's represent that thing, and we'll try to store it, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So… here… How it is going to be…
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so… Coming on to this one, like the…
Grow Data Skills: So, this is, let's say, the memory address 100. And each memory block, when we are talking about it, right, this is actually a one byte, right? It is representing the…
Grow Data Skills: One byte here, right? So…
Grow Data Skills: In this case, how it is going to happen, so this is, let's say, the 100.
Grow Data Skills: This will be 101.
Grow Data Skills: 102, 103, 104.
Grow Data Skills: That 500 6, 107.
Grow Data Skills: 809… 110, 111, 112… 11… 13.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so when we actually talked about, let's say, the row one, correct?
Grow Data Skills: So, 4 bytes, correct? The starting 4 byte, if you just…
Grow Data Skills: talk about this thing, okay? So, this is something which is going to be allocated for the integer value, what was coming in, correct? So, this is the part I'm talking about, the row 1.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: This is the part I'm talking about, the… Row 1, and here.
Grow Data Skills: This will be for, let's say, the integer value we had.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? These four whites.
Grow Data Skills: Now, this 10 bytes, right, these 10 bytes.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, if we come onto this one…
Grow Data Skills: 10 bytes, 4… you name.
Grow Data Skills: You name Varkar, okay? So, this is how it is going to be, and you can see, contiguous… these are contiguous memory locations, this, this, this, this, this, this, this, okay. Now, when we say that these RDBMS are actually storing the data in proper row format.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, what does it actually mean here, right? So, the idea is very simple. Now, the next row, which is going to come here, right?
Grow Data Skills: The next row which is going to come here, that is simply going to get started with the next immediate memory location, wherever you have stored the row 1,
Grow Data Skills: wherever it is ending, it is going to get start to store from that point onward. So, this is the memory address, let's say 113, so…
Grow Data Skills: The next one is going to be 114, let's say.
Grow Data Skills: 114, 115, 116, 117, 118, 119,
Grow Data Skills: 20, 21, 22, 23, 124, 125, 126, 127. So, whatever will be the row 2.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Whatever is going to be the row to here.
Grow Data Skills: Right? That is simply going to get started from here. So, now, again, the next…
Grow Data Skills: Here, 4 bytes for the integer value, and the next 10 bytes for the uname, whatever you are actually going to store in the
Grow Data Skills: Varkar.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, this is how it is actually going to work, and when we will actually move on to the NoSQL databases, right? So there, I will jump onto the difference between the columnar databases, because
Grow Data Skills: when you talk about the data engineering and the analytics perspective, so these IDBMS are actually not a good fit for the analytical queries, and when we talk about the analytical queries, means
Grow Data Skills: those kind of complex queries which you are running on top of a, like, 100GB, 200GB, 500GB of the data, and continuously doing the aggregates, like the joins, the conditional aggregates, group by, etc.
Grow Data Skills: In that case, these RDBMS are not performant enough.
Grow Data Skills: So, your question will be, then, what is the use case where you are actually leveraging these RDBMS? So, these RDBMS are the good fit for the use cases where you need a consistent database.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Consistent database, and you want to maintain that level of the, concurrency as well, and most importantly, right, solving the…
Grow Data Skills: like, real-time writes and updates and the CRUD operations, basically, on top of the database. If your use case is like that, where heavily you are inserting, updating, deleting the things, then obviously you need that kind of
Grow Data Skills: relational database where these things are pretty much faster, right? And most importantly, maintaining the consistency part as well.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So that is the place where these RDBMS comes into picture. Very good example is the banking and financial systems, right?
Grow Data Skills: whatever is happening, your transactions may succeed, may fail as well, so maintaining that level of consistency and proper ACID properties, right, when your use cases are like that, you prefer these transactional databases.
Grow Data Skills: These RDBMS are not at all used for your dashboarding, and you do not expose these things to the data analyst that, hey, just keep on running your join and the group by queries, because if you have 100GB data stored in this RDBMS, and you are running
Grow Data Skills: the aggregate query, group by query, it is going to take hours and hours and hours to get completed, right? Whereas if it is the columnar-based storage, or other effective and efficient database which is storing the data in that particular form.
Grow Data Skills: There, it can give you the slightly better performance. And when we talk about the analytical use cases, that is the reason we have the data warehouses and the lake house architectures in the data engineering pipeline patterns, because
Grow Data Skills: when we work on those kind of pipelines, we prefer data warehouses if the use case is the analytics, right? So that they can run the queries which are very complex, and data will get processed in the distributed manner by those data warehouses.
Grow Data Skills: In these RDBMS, it's not about the distributed computation at all. It's all about the sequential processing, like if you are doing a group by on a salary column, and imagine, this is your salary column.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So first, your read pointer will go onto this particular column, and will pick the value of salary, which is 100. Now it will iterate on all these memory blocks, and will reach to this another salary column from the row 2, where the value is 200, will take a plus, and will keep on moving, will keep on moving, will keep on moving, if you have 10 million rows, 100 million rows.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, that is why these row-based or…
Grow Data Skills: the typical RDBMS are not at all a good fit for any sort of analytics. Good fit for the web applications, maintaining the databases, you are looking at the consistency, you are looking at the faster write operations, CRUD operations, your preferred choice is the RDBMS.
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Grow Data Skills: So, now let's look onto this part.
Grow Data Skills: Cool, jeeee…
Grow Data Skills: Okay, there is a question around car, where car can store only 10 characters, but how we will assign per roads?
Grow Data Skills: Where it stores only the actual string length plus a small of it.
Grow Data Skills: So, yeah, I think…
Grow Data Skills: I forgot to clarify this part, but let me make it very simple. So, your discussion is correct, right? When we talk about the workar, when you talk about a simple car, right, I should have put a car there, not a var car, actually. So, car means fixed character. The 10 length, it is a 10 length. But when you talk about the var car, and whatever length you mention, so what does it actually mean?
Grow Data Skills: The maximum length can go up to 10 characters, but let's say, if you have mentioned var character 10, and you are storing, let's say, value amit, which is of 4 characters, so in the backend, right, in the backend of the memory, it is going to take 4
Grow Data Skills: memory blocks, plus few… maybe one and two more memory blocks to keep some sort of overhead, not more than that, okay? So that is how the worker performs.
Grow Data Skills: And the performance of care is very straightforward. Whatever number you define, 1020, multiplied by 1 byte means fixed number of blocks it is going to occupy in the memory. With var care, whatever length you are giving, it will consider maximum length can go up to that one, but in the memory, when you are storing the data, it will see what is the length of
Grow Data Skills: That string, and physically, it will allocate only those bytes for that particular worker.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? I hope it is clear now, and there is no confusion.
Grow Data Skills: So, total byte, for example, the example I took for that Amit one, okay? So, if I change var to car, that calculation is correct, 14 byte, right? So, imagine it in this way, when you change var to where, the calculation we did, it is absolutely fine. But yeah, if you…
Grow Data Skills: take workar and keep Amit there, so 4 byte plus 4 byte, means 8 byte, and imagine 1 and 2 more memory blocks as a overhead. So, approximately 8 to 10 physical storage, but it will keep a maximum buffer of 10 bytes for a particular worker, because max it can go up to that thing.
Grow Data Skills: Got it? Still any confusion?
Grow Data Skills: If you define work at 10, and you give 10 characters, it will allocate 10 ones. It will only keep 10s.
Grow Data Skills: then it will not consider anything related to the overhead, right, at all. The overhead, it is considering when the length is lesser than the actual defined length of it. Then, in that case, it keeps that, the thing related to the overhead, not when you are actually giving the full length character.
Grow Data Skills: Cool. Okay.
Grow Data Skills: So, we have created the table, perfect. So, now can, so, in which category this particular command is going to fall in, create table if not exist.
Grow Data Skills: This is going to fall in under the…
Grow Data Skills: DDL, right? Because what we are doing here, okay, so in this case, it is actually going to…
Grow Data Skills: impact the structure, or the blueprint of the table, right? So, this is going to fall under the DDL.
Grow Data Skills: So, create table, we have seen. Now, after creating the table, what we actually do.
Grow Data Skills: Right? We simply try to insert the data, okay? So let's work on that.
Grow Data Skills: So, how we can ingest the data row by row, manually, if we have to insert something, okay? What is the syntax for it? How does it work? So, there are multiple syntaxes for it, and we will iterate on them one by one.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so let's look at this part.
Grow Data Skills: Syntax 1.
Grow Data Skills: insert into. So, whenever, manually, you want to ingest maybe one record, more than one record, this is how we basically write the command for it. So, insert into reserved keywords, and then you mention the table name, which is employees.
Grow Data Skills: So, insert into employees, and after that, right, what you can simply do.
Grow Data Skills: You can mention the values here.
Grow Data Skills: And after that, inside this values, right, you simply need to provide the values in the same sequence of the table structure. And once I will talk about
Grow Data Skills: two, three syntaxes of it, you will get a better clarity. What do I actually mean with that? So, insert into employees.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So here, if you look at the table structure or the blueprint, it is ID column, then we have an employee name, then we have a salary, and then we have a hiring date. Okay? So the first value I'm going to put here, 1, which is the ID.
Grow Data Skills: And then second is of this employee name, right? VarCar, correct?
Grow Data Skills: And then, the third one is the salary, let's say $1,000. And now, talking about the hiring date, although it is of the date, data type, but whenever we talk about the ingestion and the retrieval of the date.
Grow Data Skills: it goes with the single parenthesis itself, right? A typical string kind of formation, it will look like, but in the backend, when it get stored, or when you will apply the date-related functions, they will work as it is, okay? So here, I have to insert the joining date, so let's say…
Grow Data Skills: 2021, 0, 9, and 15, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, now if I just run this thing… Okay?
Grow Data Skills: So… This is fine, okay? This command got executed. Where is that resultant?
Grow Data Skills: Okay, we didn't get… yeah, so here you can see query completed.
Grow Data Skills: So, that is how this insert command had… has got executed. If there was any failure or something, we would have got it. But, we have inserted the row, and now… first thing. First thing first.
Grow Data Skills: Right? In which particular category this is going to fall in, this is going to fall in under the DML, right? Because what we are doing, we are actually doing the data manipulation. So, insert means inserting some data, so this is going to fall under the DML.
Grow Data Skills: So, insert into employees, values, you can see, right? This one, this one.
Grow Data Skills: And whatever is the blueprint, accordingly, we have given.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So, now if you just want to look at what kind of data you have in your particular table, so there we can simply run a DQL command, which is the select statement, right? So, select
Grow Data Skills: And what I want to do, I want to look at all the columns, right, in the particular table, right? So look at all the particular columns means star.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? And then, from which particular table we want to read, so we mention keyword from.
Grow Data Skills: And then, the particular table name. So why I used it? Because I could show you the outputs
Grow Data Skills: As well. That's why I have to explain about the DQL here. So, select is your DQL, basically. So, star, when you mention star, means
Grow Data Skills: whatever is getting generated by the query plan, be it, let's say you have done some joins, group, etc, whatever will be the final result is getting generated, you are picking all the output columns of it. So that's why we mentioned the star here.
Grow Data Skills: And here, when we mention select star from the table name, means select all the columns from the employees table, and that will be our final projection.
Grow Data Skills: So if I just execute it.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So you can see, this is the output we are getting here.
Grow Data Skills: Correct?
Grow Data Skills: So, so far, we are good.
Grow Data Skills: Now, let's look at the second syntax, correct?
Grow Data Skills: what I'm going to do here now…
Grow Data Skills: Employees.
Grow Data Skills: And after that…
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Grow Data Skills: So… maybe… this thing.
Grow Data Skills: 2, comma, Shahul, comma.
Grow Data Skills: 20, 21.
Grow Data Skills: 0, 9, 15, okay?
Grow Data Skills: This is what I'm going to insert now.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So… you can see here, and if I just execute it.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, now, in this case, you can see…
Grow Data Skills: right, what has happened? Insert into this particular has failed, and some error. So let's copy this thing, copy row, and understand the error message here.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Insert this one, error code, column count does not match value count as at row 1. Okay? So, why I'm telling it? When you are actually writing this insert command in this way, insert into employees.
Grow Data Skills: So, what it is expecting, that the values you are going to provide, and the sequence of the values, they are actually following the
Grow Data Skills: table structure. But here, if you look at this part, what we did, insert into employees values.
Grow Data Skills: So, ID part is fine, means to… and then Rahul for employee name is fine, but if you look at the table structure, third column was expected to be as salary.
Grow Data Skills: And since we, as I mentioned in the beginning, very simple table, I did not put any sort of, integrity constraint, default value, etc. So that means this column was expecting some value, correct?
Grow Data Skills: And now, since I just mentioned the table name, so in the insert command, mentioning the table name means you are supposed to
Grow Data Skills: provide the values for all the column counts you have in thy structure, if there is no specific, let's say, constraint you have applied, correct?
Grow Data Skills: So now, in this case, what I did, till this point, everything is good. But the third column, as per the structure, it was salary. But what I'm giving here, I am giving this thing, the date one.
Grow Data Skills: So, that's why the error message says column count does not match value count. So, as per the table structure, it has the 4 column of the sequence. But when I'm giving the value, right, I am missing one. That is why it has failed this particular execution and did not allow me to insert this thing.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So this is the syntax, too, I wanted to explain.
Grow Data Skills: Now, let's come to that scenario, where your question is.
Grow Data Skills: let's say I don't even know about the salary of Rahul, right? But at least I know his name, I know his ID, I know his joining date, at least let me insert this data in the database.
Grow Data Skills: And whenever I will get to know about the salary of Rahul, I will simply update the… I will simply update the same thing in the database, right?
Grow Data Skills: So, that is what's simply expected.
Grow Data Skills: But, since we are following this syntax, it is not allowing me to do that. So, in this situation, what we can do?
Grow Data Skills: For an example.
Grow Data Skills: In this particular table, I just want to insert the data in specific columns, in just specific columns.
Grow Data Skills: So, in that case, what do you need when you're writing your insert command? After your table name, just define the column sequence with respect to their names.
Grow Data Skills: And in the values, follow the same sequence and pattern, and you will be able to insert it. Okay? So, how that is going to happen? So, insert into…
Grow Data Skills: employees, and I just want to insert the data. So, actually, this is the table reference name, and after that, in the parenthesis, whatever column names, and in whatever sequence I am providing.
Grow Data Skills: In the value section, I simply need to provide it in the same sequence. That's it. Okay? So here, let's say salary column.
Grow Data Skills: And then the… employee… Name column?
Grow Data Skills: And then the ID column, correct? Only these. So, ID, employee name, and salary. So, salary, employee name, and ID, and now here, values part, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, salary, let's say $2,000.
Grow Data Skills: Comma.
Grow Data Skills: You can see, right? So here, after the table name, what reference I have given. I have simply given… this is the table name reference, and this is the column sequence, right? Which is obviously not as per the table structure, but since
Grow Data Skills: I am maintaining it here, and in the same way, I will be providing the values here as well. So, salary, employee, name, and ID, correct? So…
Grow Data Skills: Rahul?
Grow Data Skills: And ID is… 2. Okay? Now, if you just do this thing…
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so this time you can see this particular insert is succeeded.
Grow Data Skills: And now, if you run this select command, again, So, select…
Grow Data Skills: So, you can see here, now, this row is also present, but for this specific row, you can see the hiring date column is null, right? Because we did not provide any value for it, so obviously there is nothing to insert there. So, the database has kept it as null.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: Now, the third syntax, where you just want to ingest more than one rows at a time, okay? More than one rows at a time. So, how we can do that?
Grow Data Skills: So again, idea is very simple.
Grow Data Skills: That insert into employees.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, and… I will simply put these values here.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, in this situation, what you are simply going to do.
Grow Data Skills: Let's say you have written this thing, values, and after that, just put comma, and put another row. Put comma, put another row. Put comma, put another row.
Grow Data Skills: Right? You don't need to write values again and again, values, so whatever you are giving inside this one, by following the table structure or the column structure, that will get ingested. And after that, comma, and keep on giving the respective rows, and that's how it is supposed to be done.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So here you can see values, so this is the specific row I have, then comma, 4, Nitin, this is the value I have, and then 5, Kajal, this is the specific value I have. So now if I simply run this thing.
Grow Data Skills: All three records got inserted, and now if I just execute it.
Grow Data Skills: So here, you can see this is the data we have. ID, employee name, salary, hiring date, and this got inserted.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: Cool.
Grow Data Skills: So, now, let's look at the very important,
Grow Data Skills: thing of the… today's discussion, that is the…
Grow Data Skills: Integrity constraints, right? We'll now talk about the integrity constraints in the
Grow Data Skills: RDBMS, right? So, first of all, what integrity constraint is? Integrity constraint we use to maintain our
Grow Data Skills: database consistent. And the technical definition of integrity constant is this set of rules.
Grow Data Skills: Right? That when you are creating a table. So, on the table bluep… on the table blueprint itself, you are applying certain rules, because you want your data to be very, very consistent.
Grow Data Skills: Let's understand it in this way, that when you created this particular table.
Grow Data Skills: employees table, you have a salary column. So now, If I do this thing, Let's say…
Grow Data Skills: Let me put it this way.
Grow Data Skills: Sorry, not this way.
Grow Data Skills: So, as I mentioned, integrity constant set of rules to keep our database consistent throughout, okay? Now, let's say I am inserting one more record.
Grow Data Skills: Now, just tell me whether this will get ingested or not, this particular record.
Grow Data Skills: Will it fail, or will it get executed properly?
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, right, this will execute properly, correct? And we will be able to insert this row. But now, tell me from the logical and practical point of view, have you heard someone getting negative salary?
Grow Data Skills: Right? What I'm doing here, I'm putting the minus sign here. So, this does not even make sense. So, when we say that integrity constraint means certain set of rules we will apply
Grow Data Skills: on our table template, so that we are keeping our data consistent. Consistency not just means that
Grow Data Skills: obviously, that whatever was the stable state before you executed the command, it should be in a stable state, right? That is definitely correct. But the consistency part, right, another wording for this.
Grow Data Skills: that… when…
Grow Data Skills: logically, you are expecting your data to be correct, right? So, you always need to define some rule. So, now, when I will get to know about the integrity constraints, so my first
Grow Data Skills: action item will be, I will apply those set of rules. One rule I can figure out from here, that the salary column.
Grow Data Skills: I will apply one mandatory check. Whenever the data is going to get inserted, or any user is trying to insert the data, one mandatory check will be salary value should always be positive.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Means it should be greater than zero. As simple as that. Okay? That is the first thing. Similarly, there are other integrity constraints as well. So, if I have to list down.
Grow Data Skills: So, ICs, So, obviously, So, check is one integrity constraint.
Grow Data Skills: Not null is another integrity constraint, so think from this perspective now.
Grow Data Skills: that employee ID, correct? So, employee ID seems like a very important kind of attribute.
Grow Data Skills: Getting the point. And, by any chance, any user trying to insert the data, and he has kept the ID value as
Grow Data Skills: None.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, again, now that will actually impact the entire analysis. If you are doing the queries, and you are joining the data based on the employee ID column, and there are many null columns in the ID. There are many null values in the ID column, so…
Grow Data Skills: Right? It is definitely not the right way to keep our data, correct? So, in that case, when…
Grow Data Skills: I am creating this table, I will apply one integrity constraint, that ID column should not be null at all.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Should not be null at all. So, in that case, I will apply one integrity constraint, and that is named as not null. So, check not null.
Grow Data Skills: And third integrity constraint is default, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, look at this part, where… what happened here? When we did not mention anything related to the hiring date, so it has kept the value as null, correct? Now, look at this part, if you are creating the dashboard based on the hiring date. So, there will be one
Grow Data Skills: Maybe bar, if you're creating the bar chart or pie chart, one bar simply mentioned as null.
Grow Data Skills: And value may be 100 to 100. Depends how many rows are having hiring date as a null value.
Grow Data Skills: So, that is also not a right metric you are looking for. So, for example, if you do not know about the hiring date of the particular employee, just giving you the rough idea. So, at least the way the day company got established, that is a default date value, you can keep it as a
Grow Data Skills: Just default value, the hiring date.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, any default value, maybe, but some default value you can give, correct? Similarly, maybe you have a particular column, right?
Grow Data Skills: where…
Grow Data Skills: somebody is trying to not insert any value. So, default, you want to put NA, right? Let's say string column.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Tisting column, and that column name is, that column name is…
Grow Data Skills: I mean, anything. It could be related to, let's say, have you completed master's degree or something? And let's say you are a still 10th grade or 12th grade student, so obviously, I mean, no, for an example, but…
Grow Data Skills: By any chance, there is an option as well, right? You are not providing anything, even yes or no, so the default value could be NA, right? Means not applicable at all.
Grow Data Skills: So, that is the third integrity constraint. And now, coming on to the fourth one. So, unique is another integrity constraint.
Grow Data Skills: So, unique integrity constraint. So, what this constraint actually…
Grow Data Skills: mentions that when you apply a unique integrity constraint on any specific column, right, while creating the blueprint or the structure of the table, so that particular
Grow Data Skills: column cannot have the duplicate values, right? Unique integrity constraint means on whatever column you are going to apply, it will
Grow Data Skills: Not have the duplicate values at all, and… I can write it here.
Grow Data Skills: doesn't… Allow duplicate values.
Grow Data Skills: But allows… Single.
Grow Data Skills: Null. That is the thing, because there is another integrity constraint's primary key, and foreign key, which will… the primary key and foreign key constraint, we will start from the tomorrow session, but I'm talking about it, right? So, primary key and the…
Grow Data Skills: foreign key.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, check not null, default, unique, primary key, and the foreign key. So, the primary key means
Grow Data Skills: Unique value for each row.
Grow Data Skills: No duplicates.
Grow Data Skills: And it can't be null.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So that is how primary key, because a lot of time, the icebreaking question in the interviews could be that difference between the unique and primary key. So, primary key, unique value for each row.
Grow Data Skills: It cannot, right.
Grow Data Skills: it cannot allow any duplicate value, and it cannot be null at all. Whereas, when you talk about the unique, so also, right, it does not allow any duplicate values, but it allows one single null value. For an example.
Grow Data Skills: Right? 1, comma, one, Right? And 2, 3, comma 3, and null… Comma, null.
Grow Data Skills: Right? So here, 1 is duplicated, so keeping distinct value, 2 is not duplicated, having one value, 3 having one value, right? But look at multiple time nulls, so with respect to the unique constraint only, right? Imagining null is having same
Grow Data Skills: Symmetric representation in the backend.
Grow Data Skills: Right? In that case, so null, you are repeating 10 times or something, so it is considering null got duplicated maybe once, or more than once, so I'll just keep null as one unique value as well. Right? So that is how unique and primary key is different with each other.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: So…
Grow Data Skills: let's try to implement it, and try to observe it practically, how does it work? Then it will make more sense, okay? So, now what I'm going to do, I'm simply going to create one table.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? And let's apply these integrity constraints there, one by one.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, create table, if not exist, employee with constraint. This is the table name I'm keeping here.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, the first column is ID, which is of integer type.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Now, there is a name column. I am keeping it var50.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, var care 50, and here, when you talk about the integrity constraint, so first you define the column name.
Grow Data Skills: the data type, and after that, you can simply put an integrity constraint. So here, on the name column, let's say I'm going to keep an integrity constraint, which is not null. So this is first integrity constraint I have applied on the name column.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? Now, coming on to another column we have, let's say, salary.
Grow Data Skills: Of integer type.
Grow Data Skills: And hiring date.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, of the date type, and now I'm going to apply the… another integrity constraint, which is default. So, in this case, I'm going to keep the default value as 20210101.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Now…
Grow Data Skills: on this particular ID column, what I wanted to do… so I… so, there are multiple ways to apply the integrity constraint, okay? And…
Grow Data Skills: as a best practice, what you should follow, I will also discuss it in a while, okay? And eventually, we should be following that one, right? But let's focus here.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Now, on this ID column, I want to apply the unique integrity constraint. So what I will be doing here, I will simply mention unique
Grow Data Skills: Right? And on which particular column I want to apply this thing, the integrity constraint. So, unique ID.
Grow Data Skills: ID column. Similarly, let's say there was a department ID, there was, you can say.
Grow Data Skills: the manager ID, I wanted to apply, let's say, the unique integrity constraint on those as well. So I could have done it that way itself, let's say, unique department ID,
Grow Data Skills: Okay, and so on. Multiple times, I could have done it in order to apply the integrity constraint on n number of the columns. Okay? So here, I just applied the unique integrity constraints on the ID column.
Grow Data Skills: And now, I also want to apply one integrity constraint on the salary. That when salary is getting ingested, I want salary… only those records to get ingested where salary is greater than 1,000. As simple as that.
Grow Data Skills: So, for that one, I will be using check integrity constraint. So, check, and now after that, I simply need to write the expression.
Grow Data Skills: So, the check I am going to apply on a salary column, and that is…
Grow Data Skills: Check salary greater than 1,000 whenever the record is supposed to get inserted.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So first, let's execute this thing.
Grow Data Skills: So, that table is created. So, table is created now.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Now, what we are simply going to do here…
Grow Data Skills: Okay? I will be writing the command one by one, and maybe, based on this.
Grow Data Skills: Integrity constraint, you can answer that, whether it will fail, whether it will succeed, and we will verify by executing it.
Grow Data Skills: So, insert into… Employee with constraints, values, One… Comma, null.
Grow Data Skills: 3000…
Grow Data Skills: 2021, 11, 20.
Grow Data Skills: So, based on your observation, what do you feel? This…
Grow Data Skills: Is going to get succeeded, or it will fail.
Grow Data Skills: This will fail. And what is the reason behind that?
Grow Data Skills: which integrity constraint it is violating here, it is actually violating this not null integrity constraint, which we applied on the name column, because name cannot be null, right? And now you can see that
Grow Data Skills: With these integrity constraints, You are maintaining the right standard of your data in the table, right?
Grow Data Skills: If you don't have those set of rules or the integrity constraint, anyone can dump any sort of garbage, right? Negative values, null values, blah blah, which definitely you don't want, correct? So, we use integrity constraints to have, or to maintain the right standard of our data the way we actually want.
Grow Data Skills: So let's run it and see…
Grow Data Skills: So, yes, you are correct that this particular command will fail, and it got failed. The error is very simple. Error code. Column name cannot be null.
Grow Data Skills: Cool? So… Perfect.
Grow Data Skills: Now, if we talk about this record.
Grow Data Skills: this insert command. Insert into this thing, right, values1 shashang3000, whether it will succeed or it will fail.
Grow Data Skills: Why it will fail? Why you guys are in so much hurry?
Grow Data Skills: It will get succeeded, right? Because I am meeting each and every constraint here, correct? So far, we did not…
Grow Data Skills: So, this command got failed, right? So, obviously, this 1 is not present in the ID column. We are going to ingest the very first record. So, 1 name is fine, it is not null. Salary, 3000, it should be greater than 1000. So, we are meeting that constraint as well. So, all the constraints are…
Grow Data Skills: All the constraints are fine.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Fail ID not unique. Yes?
Grow Data Skills: ID is not unique, but you are getting confused. If I run the select command, the previous insert command got failed, so there is no data even for the ID column.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? If I run this thing, you will see this table is empty, right? So, obviously, we are not violating anything for the particular
Grow Data Skills: unique constraint as well, correct? We are not violating anything there.
Grow Data Skills: Because this previous one got failed. So now let's run this thing, right? So, this is…
Grow Data Skills: Cool, this got executed, we didn't see any sort of error, so let's…
Grow Data Skills: Run it. So now you can see, select command, we have… now we have one record. Okay? Perfect.
Grow Data Skills: Now, let me put another insert command and tell me what is going to happen now.
Grow Data Skills: So what about this one? Insert into employee with constraints, values 1, Rahul, 5000, and all these things.
Grow Data Skills: Right. Now, this is going to fail, correct? The reason is very simple, because on the ID column, you have applied unique as a constraint, correct? And once you apply unique as a constraint, correct? So, in that case, what is going to happen?
Grow Data Skills: You have already inserted one record where ID is 1, so unique is definitely not going to allow the duplicate values, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So let's insert it.
Grow Data Skills: So now you can see this has failed. Let's copy the command… sorry, let's copy the error message and see.
Grow Data Skills: So here you can see insert into error code, duplicate entry 1 for key. This one. This is the key.id. Duplicate entry is not allowed because we have applied the unique integrity constraint.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: Now…
Grow Data Skills: What about this one?
Grow Data Skills: This will pass. Reason is, on the ID column, we have kept the value as null. And if you remember, when you talk about the unique integrity constraint, it allows null, okay? It allows null, correct?
Grow Data Skills: So let's run it. So you can see, this is succeeded, and I can run the select command to show you the same.
Grow Data Skills: So here, you can see this record got inserted.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Now, you will see a slightly different behavior on the MySQL side, okay? Because of few reasons. But if you will run it on any other
Grow Data Skills: RDBMS, be it Oracle, Postgres, you will see that is getting failed instantly, okay? And I'll tell you why.
Grow Data Skills: So look at this part. Insert into employee values null. Now, what about this row? If I'm going to insert it… So, logically, whatever we discussed, right, what do you think? What should happen with that?
Grow Data Skills: This will fail, or this will pass.
Grow Data Skills: So, absolutely right, logically, whatever we discussed, that it will allow null values, it should fail, because it should keep one
Grow Data Skills: null value, right? But now here, as I said, from databases to databases, sometimes few behaviors may change, okay? So when you talk about the MySQL, I'm talking with respect to MySQL, what it is going to do
Grow Data Skills: So, for… on the ID column, even if you have applied the unique integrity constraint, if you will ingest 10 rows, where the ID column is null, it will accept all 10 rows, right?
Grow Data Skills: But if you run the same query on Oracle or on the Postgres, it is simply going to fail if you are trying to insert another row where the ID column is null.
Grow Data Skills: Right? It is all about how different
Grow Data Skills: SQL engine is treating a null value. So here, with respect to MySQL, what you can say…
Grow Data Skills: that these… because null is not having any particular shape here, right? Do you know any shape? What value in the backend null is keeping? It could be 10,000, 50,000, some 999 minus negative, etc, etc.
Grow Data Skills: Correct? So, every null is actually going with a different representation here. That is why, when you talk about the MySQL here, okay, it is actually accepting, going to accept all those
Grow Data Skills: rows where the ID value is null itself. But as I said, since I have tested these things and worked with different databases, so this…
Grow Data Skills: behavior, the logical…
Grow Data Skills: implementation of the unique. It works as it is when you talk about the Postgres or the Oracle, right? I have used it there as well, so I'm saying it based on that.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, when…
Grow Data Skills: This thing comes up into the interviews, so you'll be confused that what we should tell. You should simply tell what we've discussed logically, because this is sometimes database-to-database dependency, right? You don't need to go into this one, right? You simply need to stick to the logical part, that one null is going to be there.
Grow Data Skills: So if I now simply run it.
Grow Data Skills: So you can see this has succeeded, right? And now if I run it.
Grow Data Skills: you will see this row is also there. So, logically, it should have failed, right? But, as I explained the reason as well, it has passed, okay? So just keep the unique integrity constraint understanding in that way.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, now coming on to the next one.
Grow Data Skills: Which is?
Grow Data Skills: this pack.
Grow Data Skills: So, what about this? If I'm trying to insert into this one, value 5 and ameth 500, this, this, whether it will be pass or fail?
Grow Data Skills: This will fail. Why? Because it will actually violate the salary check, correct? If you remember, for salary, it must be greater than 1000. But here, the salary value is coming 500, so let's run it and validate.
Grow Data Skills: So here, you can see it has failed as well, so let's copy it and see the error message.
Grow Data Skills: So, error message says check constraint employee with constraint check 1 is violated.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Perfect.
Grow Data Skills: Now… One more.
Grow Data Skills: So what about this one? Insert into employee with this thing, ID, name, and salary, values 7 needed and 3000. Whether it is going to fail or succeed.
Grow Data Skills: This will be succeeded.
Grow Data Skills: But we are not passing anything related to date. In that case, what is going to happen?
Grow Data Skills: Yes, date will be default, means it should pick up the default value, correct? So let's execute it and verify.
Grow Data Skills: So this command got executed, and let's just run the select statement.
Grow Data Skills: So now you can see the last record which we inserted for the Neeraj.
Grow Data Skills: Right? This one. So the default value is 20210101. So default is working fine.
Grow Data Skills: Now… you remember in the beginning, I mentioned that
Grow Data Skills: I will always be following a better way to put the integrity constraint, correct?
Grow Data Skills: So look at this part.
Grow Data Skills: Right? This… this got failed, right?
Grow Data Skills: When we were actually trying to insert this record, where the salary was $500.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So, here, look at this part. Check constraint employee with constraint, check 1. So, with this message itself.
Grow Data Skills: Right? Imagine you have a very big table, 50 columns, and there are 10 columns on which you have applied the check constraint. So, with this specific name, can you tell me on which particular column did you apply the check constraint, or will it be easy for you to debug?
Grow Data Skills: Until unless you look at the table structure again and try to identify which particular
Grow Data Skills: A constraint is actually violating here.
Grow Data Skills: Because this is that dynamic name, got generated with this specific name, right? Do you have any clarity that which particular constraint got failed? No, you don't have any clarity. If out of 50 columns we have 10, how are you even going to identify that?
Grow Data Skills: Right? So that is why the best practice is when you are actually creating a table and want to apply the integrity constraint, so always define them with
Grow Data Skills: the specific name, so that you have a proper clarity of it, okay? Let me…
Grow Data Skills: Let me tell you how we are going to do that, okay? So let me copy this definition.
Grow Data Skills: And I will create another one.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so here, this is a new table I'm going to create, employee with constraints temp, right? So ID is fine, and here, name, worker, not null, salary is fine.
Grow Data Skills: This is fine. But at least look at from this perspective, and obviously, you can have the name for these ones, you can define the default constraints here as well. That is not at all an issue, right? Similarly, the not nulls as well.
Grow Data Skills: But, look at this one, unique, check, and similarly, I have 4 or 5 check constraints I want to apply.
Grow Data Skills: So, the better way to do it, because
Grow Data Skills: There could be a scenario, let's say today you created a table structure, and after some days, like, for next one week or something, you are inserting the data into it, you are doing the manipulation.
Grow Data Skills: But after some days, you realize that I need to add 2-3 more constraints on this particular table. So, obviously, we will be using the alter command, etc. for that one.
Grow Data Skills: So, how we actually do that? So, the better way is to always use a constraint keyword, and with the constraint keyword, you will always be able to give a unique name to a specific integrity constraint you are applying, okay? So, for an example, when instead of defining it in this way.
Grow Data Skills: How I will do it?
Grow Data Skills: constraint.
Grow Data Skills: And the constraint name.
Grow Data Skills: unique.
Grow Data Skills: ID, right? Unique ID IC means on this particular column, right, unique is the constraint, and ID is the… on which particular column, and IC, if you want, you can keep, or you can ignore it, but integrity constraint, correct? Now, similarly, for the
Grow Data Skills: this one, check as well. So here, what I'm going to do… Check.
Grow Data Skills: Salary, I see. Similarly, if I had, let's say, some age, age greater than 18, correct? That kind of check I wanted to apply. So, I would simply do that.
Grow Data Skills: Constraint, check.
Grow Data Skills: Age integrity constraint, and age…
Grow Data Skills: 18, correct? So, this way, you can see, you are able to provide a very specific name to your integrity constraint, and how
Grow Data Skills: easy it will be. When the integrity constraints are going to get violated or fail, in the error message, that will reflect, and instantly, you will be able to point out that, okay, this is actually failing, because the age column, we are not passing properly, or salary column, okay? So let's…
Grow Data Skills: Run it once, and try to test it as well.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so I created this table. Now what I'm going to do… I am going to insert
Grow Data Skills: the same command.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: So here, you can see what I'm doing. I'm actually violating this salary constraint, correct? So now, if I just execute this command, insert command.
Grow Data Skills: So this has failed, okay? Now if I copy… the error message.
Grow Data Skills: Look at this part, huh?
Grow Data Skills: Check constraint, check salary.
Grow Data Skills: integrity constraint. So, at least, since you have defined these things, and you are following the right pattern, right, naming conventions, and this way, it is very much easy for you to quickly point out for which particular column, etc, things are actually getting failed.
Grow Data Skills: Okay?
Grow Data Skills: Cool.
Grow Data Skills: Alright, so that is pretty much for today's session. I will just keep it till this point, okay? And, for you.
Grow Data Skills: the action items, obviously, your MySQL workbench setup, and whatever commands, right, we practiced today, executed today, I will definitely upload it in the LMS. You can refer them, you can again execute it, okay? These are the two things.
Grow Data Skills: Coming onto the… I will give you one quiz, right, just to test a few things.
Grow Data Skills: I will not give the assignment, right? And I hope you can understand it, because we just practice insert, create, and the integrity constraint, and it does not make sense what assignment I should give, like, create these 50 tables with different schema. Okay, so that is what I'm not going to do.
Grow Data Skills: to be very honest, for SQL, I have prepared a very extensive assignment, which I will give you after completing the SQL session, because
Grow Data Skills: That way, you will be able to apply all the learnings, right? Your group, you will be able to write optimal queries, group by, joins, window function, conditional aggregate, etc, whatever you have… we have used. So, I hope you guys agree with me, correct?
Grow Data Skills: like, giving the dedicated assignment after completing all the topics of SQL, that will make more sense, rather than I'm giving 10 questions for group by, 10 questions for join, 10 questions for create table, it will not make sense, correct?
Grow Data Skills: So…
Grow Data Skills: quizzes, I will keep on giving, right, so that you can just validate few things with respect to the learnings, etc. Rest, it should be fine, okay?
Grow Data Skills: Cool, alright. So, yeah, that is pretty much for today, and yeah. After…
Grow Data Skills: 2 to 3 hours, this, like, recording for the today's session, and all the content resources I was talking about, it will be available on your LMS, you can refer it and access it, okay? Now, if you have any queries and questions, so raise your hands, I will unmute you, and you can ask your doubt.
Grow Data Skills: And to take the maximum outcome from this bootcamp, it would be always better and highly recommended from my side.
Grow Data Skills: If…
Grow Data Skills: you can keep your doubts around the topic-related discussions, right? I know many of you might be having doubts related to your career, you are maybe in some specific, let's say, job profile, how I should do it. We have a 4-month long journey, and for all these kind of detailed discussion, just slide into personal DM of Discord.
Grow Data Skills: Right? In detail, I will help you related to career guidance, because
Grow Data Skills: These sessions, the doubt should be related to the topic we are covering today, and maybe when we are
Grow Data Skills: we have covered 2-3 weeks, and you have the topics related… doubts related to the previous topics, etc, right? Or any technical question you want to ask, so that would be much better. I would highly appreciate that thing.
Grow Data Skills: And if you don't have any doubt, feel free to leave. You can drop off, you can enjoy your rest of the day, because now I'm not going to teach anything new, it's just the doubt discussion, that's it. So anyone who is dropping off, thanks for joining, and we will meet tomorrow.
Grow Data Skills: Cool, cool. Alright, so now let me stop sharing my screen, and one by one, I will…
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so I will just unmute you one by one, and you can ask your doubts.
Grow Data Skills: Do we get… so, interview preparation guide and the assignment, Anjali, as I mentioned, I will just give at the end of the SQL module, right? So that you can practice it.
Grow Data Skills: I mean, for the SQL, interviews are more about, sometimes technically, like, views, indexes, how do you optimize SQL queries, etc, but more it is about the SQL problem statement, how do you practice it, okay? I will give a very detailed assignment for it, having, like, approximately 100, 120 questions across different categories.
Grow Data Skills: Assignments will be… the assignments will be exactly the same way I am creating the SQL series on the Instagram, so it is going to be in a similar way, that level of questions you'll be getting.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, so now if you have any questions, when the timing, topic, etc, so simply just open your…
Grow Data Skills: course landing page and get all these details. I am not going to repeat these details again, because it is already there, and in the indexing session, I already mentioned these things in detail, right? So, please avoid asking repetitive questions.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, now let me see…
Grow Data Skills: Okay, first is Tapa Breath. Hey, Tapa Breath, I hope I have pronounced your name correctly.
Tapabrata Halder: Yeah, yeah, yeah. So, I have a question, like, you are showing us, like, how to connect it here. I tried to connect SQL Workbench, to a MySQL in the AWS.
Tapabrata Halder: And it's not happening, I mean, it's not working. The same thing when I'm trying to…
Grow Data Skills: Sorry, can you repeat one more time?
Tapabrata Halder: So I created a database.
Tapabrata Halder: the, AWS, posted in AWS, and tried to connect to… through that, I mean, through this.
Grow Data Skills: You have a MySQL database already created in your local, right?
Tapabrata Halder: not local, in AWS.
Grow Data Skills: AWS, okay, and you are trying to connect, but it is not connecting.
Tapabrata Halder: connecting. It's giving, some…
Tapabrata Halder: I mean, access not granted something, some types of error like that. But the same database, when I'm trying to connect through Blue, it is connecting.
Tapabrata Halder: I mean, I am very new to AWS, that's why I'm getting this issue.
Grow Data Skills: No, so that is fine. I think it would be better because there are a few things. When you set up a transaction, I mean, RDS instance on AWS,
Grow Data Skills: To set up that connectivity, you need to just go to the security layer and expose the port as well, so that the any incoming requests, connectivity requests.
Grow Data Skills: from wherever you are sending, right, it can get accepted. If you are not allowing those things in the security group, right, you are not allowing that thing in the inbound group.
Tapabrata Halder: I got it. I think my access… I got only private access there.
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, yeah.
Tapabrata Halder: So you need to enable that. And a second question, if I want to… I mean, I want to master in data modeling.
Tapabrata Halder: How should I progress?
Tapabrata Halder: I want to learn data modeling fully. Even though I am an architect, that's the weakest point I have.
Grow Data Skills: So, see, focusing more on the data modeling is all about, the, let's say, fact dimensions and the snowflake schema, star and galaxies. That eventually is going to come from
Grow Data Skills: your multiple practical questions you are looking at, right? So the best way is to pick
Grow Data Skills: right, this is my approach, I have practiced it in that way, that pick various data domains, because when you go into the interviews, right, these things may come up in a different way, right?
Grow Data Skills: The, let's say, how we are going to…
Grow Data Skills: design a data model for a ride-sharing application, how we are going to design a data model for the healthcare application, similarly for e-commerce, fintech, travel, and hospitality. So, pick various domains, right?
Grow Data Skills: Because there is no fixed pattern of it, first of all, right? And when you go into the interviews, you do not design the most optimal data model, you just touch base on it based on the business KPIs the interviewer has.
Tapabrata Halder: No, I'm not asking in terms of interviews. Interview, I can handle, I know. But I'm trying, like, mastering that particular thing, like.
Tapabrata Halder: So, even though I have a human experience in data modeling also.
Grow Data Skills: CC, see, listen to me. Without practicing, how do you master anything?
Tapabrata Halder: Yeah, yeah, that's what I'm telling you. Which way?
Grow Data Skills: That's what I was explaining. That's what I was explaining. If you want to master it, so how many different data domains, data model, have you created as of now?
Tapabrata Halder: Mostly, I worked on retail and manufacturing, so my experience.
Grow Data Skills: So, that is.
Tapabrata Halder: What is wine?
Grow Data Skills: that is why, because your data domain knowledge is limited towards that direction, so you will be effectively able to create the data model for it, all the fact, related dimensions and all. But your question was, how do I master it? So, mastering it, you need to touch base on the different databases as well, because
Grow Data Skills: Concept-wise, you have already mastered. Snowflake schema will be Snowflake. There are nothing additional you are going to add into that. Galaxy schema concept is Galaxy schema, right? No additions in that. But when you are designing it, you need to think from the business KPI perspective, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, when the data modeling question is given to you in the interviews.
Grow Data Skills: the interviewer will clarify that if you are designing your data model, make sure you are able to answer these business KPIs. So, always focus on those KPIs that what answers it is expecting, so that when you're designing your data model, you are not skipping adding those specific columns.
Grow Data Skills: Either in your fact or in your dimension. That's the.
Tapabrata Halder: So, I'll give you one instance. I… right now, I mean, a few days back, I was working for a retail project, B2B retail, and it… I was able to correctly design till the gold year.
Tapabrata Halder: But there is a data product layer on top of gold layer. I mean, I faced some problems there.
Tapabrata Halder: And that's because I was doing a bottom-up approach.
Tapabrata Halder: But that… I didn't able to link.
Tapabrata Halder: that, data model, and the KPIs didn't come properly, so… And nowadays, like, previously we used to create till reporting layer, right? But nowadays, those things also pushed into the database, right? They are asking to create data products, they're asking…
Grow Data Skills: Yes, certainly.
Tapabrata Halder: Yeah, metric view, like, data brief supports metric view also. So, these kinds of things, where can I get proper details?
Grow Data Skills: There is no proper resource for it.
Tapabrata Halder: Okay.
Grow Data Skills: Right? There is no proper… if there was a resource, you might not even ask this question to me, because you would… you would have found it, you would have practiced it. So that's why I said.
Grow Data Skills: I have kept a dedicated data modeling module itself, where those practical case studies are there. Plus, when we will move on to, let's say, the Databricks, the Snowflake module specifically.
Grow Data Skills: and the project part itself. So, obviously, we are going to do a proper modeling there, right? It's not like one big fat table I'm going to keep, and I will dump every data there. So, having the right data model for it, so maybe once we reach there, you will get little more clarity, but at your experience level, as I mentioned. So don't keep your focus towards the retail kind of data domain.
Grow Data Skills: But just move towards the different data domain.
Grow Data Skills: Pick it up, right? And if you want more…
Grow Data Skills: interview kind of feel, use ChatGPT as your interviewer. Ask
Grow Data Skills: the chat GPT to ask the cross-question to yourself, right? That I want to practice this healthcare data domain, ask the relevant data modeling question to me. So when he will start asking, right, you will have the idea of what kind of questions are going to come up in front of you.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? And for the practice perspective, I'm definitely going to give you all those kind of practical problem statements in depth once we reach on that module, and they will be from different data domains, so that you can apply those learnings, and you can simply, just understand that part, how different data domains models you can create.
Grow Data Skills: So, this is a Vaja's first session, so…
Grow Data Skills: Although I clarified that, better to keep the doubts around these topics, but yeah, once we will reach onto that one, you can have these discussions more detailed.
Tapabrata Halder: Yeah, thanks, thanks for your time.
Grow Data Skills: Cool, alright.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, next is Roshan, and I… just, before coming to you, Roshan, I saw some question on the, chat that where to find the et cetera, et cetera. So, see, this is your course LMS, right?
Grow Data Skills: once you log in onto the platform from web, from the mobile application, whatever it is. So, see, this is the place where I have listed down the steps for joining the Discord group, so follow these things.
Grow Data Skills: And this is the part where we have given our Android and iOS app link. And you can see, right, this is the program overview, or a induction session, right? I have already created for you in detail, where I have described everything related to the platform, program overview, how we are going to proceed, move, and all.
Grow Data Skills: And this is the today's class which was happening, where I have already…
Grow Data Skills: added the workbench setup related links, you can follow, and today's class recording will be available here, and the notes, the particular, the SQL commands we were using, they will also get uploaded here. You will be able to check it out here, okay? So now, I hope, from today onwards, these questions will not come up.
Grow Data Skills: Because you have not invested time to explore the platform itself, so use today's day and just do that, so that from today, you are not asking these kind of repetitive and, very basic type of questions.
Grow Data Skills: what is the purpose of creating an instance at the very beginning? So, instance, I mean, if you want to practice anything, Faraham.
Grow Data Skills: So, how would you do that? I mean, you'd need to have a MySQL instance to practice and run these SQL queries.
Grow Data Skills: Next is Roshan. Hey, Roshan.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: Yeah, hi, Shishang. Shishang, I have a question on integrity constructs, which you have mentioned.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: So, previously we mentioned that, we have… we defined the integrity comes back, Who…
ROSHAN SATPATHY: to, you know, by default, like, if I'm putting this,
ROSHAN SATPATHY: date as a default, or ID as a domic.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: Or something… So…
ROSHAN SATPATHY: That way, we can put the integrity constants, and we can get the output. But what is the use of that constant, before using this integrity constant?
ROSHAN SATPATHY: Let it get quality.
Grow Data Skills: No, I… okay, no, I didn't understand the last statement. What is the use of?
ROSHAN SATPATHY: Constant. You have mentioned the start constant.
Grow Data Skills: constraint keyword, which I used.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, so, yeah, I mean, because…
Grow Data Skills: when you are writing it without that keyword, right? Just, you are simply using the main constraint, let's say unique, okay, and then the check, etc, etc. But when you have to give a specific name to any specific, let's say, integrity constraint.
Grow Data Skills: In that case, you… like, we were using create table, and then table name. So, if you want to create a table, you have to follow that fixed pattern of create table keywords. So, if you want to give a very specific name to any specific integrity constraint you are writing, you need to follow that syntax pattern, like constraint keyword, then constraint name, and then the value of the constraint.
Grow Data Skills: So it's a fixed, like, pattern and syntax we need to follow.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: So what if I'm not using that constant keyword?
Grow Data Skills: If you will not.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: apparently…
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, if you will not use the constraint keyword, then the issue I was talking about, the SQL engine, right, it will automatically create some random dynamic name for the constraint you have created, not the unique name you are providing there. So it will have that impact.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: But previously, when we create table, Susan, for that employee with constraint, right? So, when I put the, you know, the name and everything.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: And previously, I defined that the integer ID will be the integer, and the salary will be the integer, hiring date will be the default, unique ID will be the unique ID name.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: So… I'm getting the output which I needed, right?
Grow Data Skills: So you are… no, so don't think in that way what you are getting, you need it. Think from the other's perspective as well, right? You have written, you have created table, you know about the entire structure. Think about another data engineer who's new to the team, and he starts using your table, and you have…
Grow Data Skills: the, table of 100 columns, and you have applied a check constraint without any unique name to different, different columns, right? So, in that case, if that particular guy
Grow Data Skills: Okay? Not… If you… that particular guy is basically running the query.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? And simply running it, correct? So, in that case, what is going to happen, right? In that case, it will get violated, and it… that particular guy will not have any idea, by looking at the error message for which particular column this integrity constraint has failed.
Grow Data Skills: Because the random name is getting generated.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: Got it. So, the purpose of this constant keyword is, like, every… if a person, XYZ, is
ROSHAN SATPATHY: go through that table and find the, find out the error. So this, when we put this constant keyword, it will…
ROSHAN SATPATHY: If the error is coming, it will specify the specific error which
ROSHAN SATPATHY: it is, the person is getting, right? We will get to know, right, like, where is the exact error.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: It is… Providing by the… Notes. Several.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: Is that right?
Grow Data Skills: Yes, yes, yes.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: Okay, okay.
ROSHAN SATPATHY: Thank you, Shalman. That's my question.
Grow Data Skills: Thank you, yeah.
Grow Data Skills: So, question from Vijay. There are, yes, multiple RDBMS. Thus, can we practice or get to know the difference among these systems along learning?
Grow Data Skills: That will be a little bit hard, Vijay, because that might create the slight confusion. So, when I started this MySQL module, my intention was simple. I will stick to that one.
Grow Data Skills: And as I mentioned, there is not a very huge level of difference, very slight differences, with respect to the function levels, most of the time, right? Function level, data type levels, rest the query pattern, be it the group biologic, the joins, etc, window functions, that is, like, same overall, okay? So that is how it is, so…
Grow Data Skills: If along the class, right, I start focusing on all 3 or 4 type of syntaxes, it will be hard for other people sometimes to catch up and understand. They might, get mistaken at a lot of places.
Grow Data Skills: Hmm, okay.
Grow Data Skills: Next is Abhishek.
Abhishek: Yeah, hi, Sushin.
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Abhishek: So, I have, in general question related to Python. Like, I have two questions. One is, like, as a data engineer, like, where all we will be using the Python?
Abhishek: And, second is related to interview perspective. Like, if I'm preparing for data engineering interview, till what area should I practice Python?
Grow Data Skills: Okay, good question. So, with respect to Python, see, majority of the time,
Grow Data Skills: So, there are two, three aspects when you talk about the Python. So, let's start from the interview perspective, right? So, from interview perspective, I mean, whatever foundational layer of the Python you know, in the interviews, they are not going to ask you to code something on Panda's library, use it, show me, etc, etc. They don't do it.
Grow Data Skills: They simply keep focused on the generic problem solving, right? Could be easy, medium level of DSA question, based on the array, string, stack, queue, etc, etc. Not on the hard level, like the tree graph, or heap, etc, but…
Grow Data Skills: easy, medium level, and they ask you to simply solve it. So, in that case, you just keep your focus on the foundational layer of Python, like working with loops, working with the lambda expressions, dictionary, list, tuples, list comprehension, dictionary comprehensions.
Grow Data Skills: Right? And how do you logically solve any problem with the help of Python? Okay? So that is the one thing.
Grow Data Skills: Coming onto the day-to-day activities of a data engineer. So, at multiple places you are going to use. So, specifically, let's say your tech stack is PySpark itself, okay? So, here, you are simply using the PySpark, I mean, the Spark library built on top of the Python wrapper, okay? So, there, you are actually using it.
Grow Data Skills: And you are, like, like, writing more and more code in the Python, but there, you're…
Grow Data Skills: the kind of Python you are writing, it is specific to the PySpark library. You are not writing a standard or standalone Python script, okay, but utilizing the PySpark library methods and all, and processing the data. So that is the second way, majority of the time, data engineers will be using. The third thing is
Grow Data Skills: write Python, where it may come up, in picture of…
Grow Data Skills: The… if you are doing some sort of ad hoc automations or scripting-level task, okay? That is the third place.
Grow Data Skills: Fourth place could be if you are using the Airflow, right? So, in the Airflow, when we basically create the DAG, so that entire coding is done in the Python, where we follow Airflow-related libraries, and we simply create various operators and their dependencies, okay? So…
Grow Data Skills: Considering these points, the oops-level understanding, not maybe the complete deep dive, but
Grow Data Skills: how do you even create a class? How do you define the constructor? How do you define multiple methods, attributes, right? In the Python, that understanding is needed, because a lot of time when you use libraries, for an example, right, when we will reach onto the Kafka module.
Grow Data Skills: We will be writing our producers, consumers, using the Kafka libraries.
Grow Data Skills: And it will be in Python, so we will be using multiple classes of the Kafka library, objects of it, attribute of it, methods of it. So you need to know, have that understanding, how do you work with the oops concept on the Python part. So this level of Python expertise, right, is definitely good enough.
Grow Data Skills: Right, for your day-to-day activities as a data engineer.
Abhishek: And from that interview perspective, till the basic level of,
Grow Data Skills: Very foundational level. In the interviews, no need to go on, like, if you have your interview scheduled after 2 days, right? No need to brush up anything related to oops and all. Focus on the native data structures of the Python, and obviously more focus towards the problem solving.
Grow Data Skills: Hey, Akul, please.
Grow Data Skills: If you have a question, as I mentioned in the beginning, raise your hand, and once your turn will be there, I will unmute you. I can't let you in randomly in between, okay? So, have that patience, and please ask the questions in the right way.
Grow Data Skills: Oh, yeah, Abhishe, go ahead.
Abhishek: Yeah, that's it from mine. Thank you.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, thank you.
Grow Data Skills: Next is Shubadhi.
Grow Data Skills: Hey, Shubhadeep.
Grow Data Skills: Hello?
Subhadip Chatterjee: Hey, hi, Sam, how are you?
Grow Data Skills: Hey, I'm good, thank you.
Subhadip Chatterjee: Okay. So, Sagan, my question will be based on this care data type. So, as, I understood, like, in var care, if I mention, like, VarCare, and up to 10, if I use, then 4 bytes will be used, and then over will be 1 or 2.
Subhadip Chatterjee: But in the care data type, like,
Grow Data Skills: In the CAR data type, it will be fixed, right? I mean, if I have created CAR10, and I'm just storing one character in that particular column, so in that case, entire 10 bytes will be occupied, that is the concept of CAR, the fixed length. When you talk about var care, means it's a variable
Grow Data Skills: like, length for the character data type, and whatever length you define, so maximum, it can go up to that one, right? But if you are storing any value less than that one, so based…
Grow Data Skills: on that variable aspect, right? Physically, it will allocate those a specific number of bytes for the particular value you are giving.
Subhadip Chatterjee: So, even though we are using or not using, that doesn't… that does not matter, right? Like, if I… if I use, if I, mention Cat 10, and I'm not using the 10, characters, so that also will be using total 6 length we'll be using.
Grow Data Skills: Now, in that case, right, so, in that case, what it is going to do, right, it will not… it is not going to utilize it, right? It is not going to utilize that specific space, right? The particular, let's say, 10 bytes were there.
Grow Data Skills: So, when you gave only 4 characters, so physical allocation is going to be the 4 bytes here. The rest of the remaining bytes can be utilized by the others.
Subhadip Chatterjee: Okay, understood.
Subhadip Chatterjee: Well, thank you.
Grow Data Skills: Cool.
Grow Data Skills: Next is Saurabh.
Grow Data Skills: Hi, Shot up.
Grow Data Skills: Hello?
Shorab: Now, now I'm audible.
Shorab: Hope I'm…
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, yeah, yeah, I can hear you.
Shorab: Yeah, my question is, like, we are using a lot of constants. So, let's say we have a table and which is having huge columns, and if we apply constants, then it might impact the performance, right?
Grow Data Skills: So, performance-wise, absolutely, right? Because when you are inserting the data, so the checks, obviously, and when you are inserting every row, it will look at all the columns, right? And specifically, whatever checks you have applied.
Grow Data Skills: But, as I mentioned in, earlier as well, here you are not looking at the performance. Here, I mean, you know this drawback that
Grow Data Skills: there are 10 column, 20 column, and I'm applying the check on each and every column. There will be performance issues during the insert part, right? But…
Grow Data Skills: the advantage you are getting here, the data consistency. And that is the whole and sole purpose of having the integrity constraint. Nothing related to that, I want to degrade the performance, or I just want to optimize something, but if the data consistency and the data contract or the data standard is important enough.
Grow Data Skills: Then you have to just go ahead with that way, considering that's some more millisecond of delay because of those constraint checks in the backend.
Shorab: Thanks.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, next is Ravi.
Grow Data Skills: Hi, Ravi.
Grow Data Skills: Hello?
Grow Data Skills: Hey, Ravi, I'm not able to hear you if you're speaking.
Ravi Shekhawat: Hello, can you hear me now?
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, I can hear you now. Please go ahead.
Ravi Shekhawat: Hi, Shishak. So, first thing I wanted to ask was, when you talked about a machine, in the example of that MySQL is being set up on a machine, that was EC2?
Grow Data Skills: No, no, that wasn't a EC2, but with respect to AWS, even if I'm spinning up an RDS instance, right, so the underlying foundational layer is definitely the EC2, where… because it's a managed service, right?
Grow Data Skills: If I have to do it with that traditional way, obviously I can have a EC2 instance, setting up the MySQL there, and then setting up the whole connectivity layer. But if I just want to go ahead with the manage layer, right, where maybe it is giving me other options as well, like auto backup, all other aspects, and just configuring it based on
Grow Data Skills: the… Based on the volume I might be expecting, so…
Grow Data Skills: It will just give us those configuration options, and we can simply set up the whole database, and it will do the installation of MySQL on its own, and will give me the up and running instance, without bothering about all other EC2 instances sort of things.
Ravi Shekhawat: Perfect.
Ravi Shekhawat: Another thing was, let's say, there's a team, and I have to set things up for them, and there are going to be multiple people who will be working.
Grow Data Skills: Right.
Ravi Shekhawat: on that database. So, what is the more swifter, smarter way to set things up for people? Like, if there are a number of people?
Grow Data Skills: Correct. So, I'll… I'll… and that's a good question. So, I will put it in the… this way, based on experiences. Because when you work, right, in an organization.
Grow Data Skills: And if you are just a data engineer, let's say, correct? So, 99% of the time, these setup-related things are not in your hand, okay? Because companies have a dedicated ops team, DevOps team, cloud admin, admin, DBA, who are actually going to take this responsibility.
Grow Data Skills: Whenever you probably need any table, you need any access or anything, right? It actually goes from a proper business approval process.
Grow Data Skills: you raise a ticket to the infra team, or the ops team, hey, I need access on these, these things, or I need to get created these things, or I want a dedicated dev instance for myself, because I need to do a POC. So you raise everything, and the infra team is going to create, allocate everything for you.
Grow Data Skills: And you will have a…
Grow Data Skills: the, like, appropriate, not the entire admin level of thing, but the access which are supposed to be needed to complete your POC, right? Apart from that, anything extra you want to do, you always need to go with that specific route.
Grow Data Skills: to raise a request, get that approved, because it might need a business approval, and then it will happen. So, even in my 10 years of experience, wherever I have been so far, except these startups, right? Like Prophecy, and currently.
Grow Data Skills: Right, when I'm working. So, there, it is more about…
Grow Data Skills: owning the things, right? And specifically, even till the dev level, not even in the production and all. There, as well, you sit with the architect, right? And with the infra team, you design your whole pipeline architecture pattern. Then, whatever you need, first you need it, or you do it on the dev level, and then, accordingly, you raise the similar request to productionize your thing in the production, and have the right resources.
Grow Data Skills: Created by the infrared team accordingly. This is how it works in the company.
Grow Data Skills: That's how it is.
Ravi Shekhawat: All right. So, actually, Shashank, I asked this because I'm getting in a lot of fights with DevOps guys, because of…
Grow Data Skills: Correct. So, yeah, I can understand your pain point, because sometimes you just want to expedite the things, correct? And, I mean, the better way, I'm not really sure if your company has given you the dev account, so at least in that one, you have
Grow Data Skills: some sort of liberty to spin up, right? Maybe in a limited capacities and all, and maybe directly you can have a conversation with your manager to bypass and to get expedite the things, but this is what it is, right? A lot of time, people who are part of this bootcamp, who are new to this thing, they will have a curiosity, okay, when I will get into the company, I will
Grow Data Skills: take everything in my own hand, will spin up everything as I need. So, guys, it is not… it does not work in that way, alright? I'll be very transparent. So, why I'm teaching you here? So that you have the clarity that
Grow Data Skills: you are not just having the idea how to use it, but how to actually create it as well, so that if you have to do your own projects as well, and you have your own AWS account, etc, at least you can do that.
Ravi Shekhawat: Alright.
Ravi Shekhawat: So, Shishank, whenever you get into a new industry and there is a lot of new context.
Ravi Shekhawat: For example, I get a lot of problems when it comes to
Ravi Shekhawat: getting clear expectations from architect or anybody. So there is a lot of bad documentation at times, not-so-clear scenarios and situations.
Ravi Shekhawat: basically not enough of information to work on, but results are expected. How to navigate through such situations, because the documentation is not there.
Grow Data Skills: So, can you explain the last part one more time?
Ravi Shekhawat: okay, so…
Grow Data Skills: There was some… there was some audio disturbance, so I couldn't hear the last part.
Ravi Shekhawat: So, mmm… I am suffering with unclear expectations about the.
Grow Data Skills: Clear expectations.
Ravi Shekhawat: And, for example, where the sources might be, what kind of…
Ravi Shekhawat: data source am I really going to work with? Who is the concerned person I need to reach out to work with?
Grow Data Skills: Right.
Ravi Shekhawat: So, how to work around such real-world problems?
Grow Data Skills: Cutting.
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, totally agree on that part. So, sometimes it is easy to get, sometimes it is hard to get.
Grow Data Skills: So, that depends what level of hierarchy sometimes is even being followed when you are working on a project, right? Because if the hierarchy is proper, for an example, because if you're directly dependent on client, no mediator in between, then that will be really, really challenging, because even to get the client's time and get that discussion
Grow Data Skills: Going on and get the clarity.
Grow Data Skills: So, I mean, this is the part where, I mean, the project manager, right, whoever is assigned, the engagement manager, who is… whoever is assigned.
Grow Data Skills: for that particular project, I think it's better to block a dedicated time, and that's my personal experience as well. I have, like, I always believe, at least, in chasing people continuously. And after doing it at least one and two times, I don't get it. I'm pretty much vocal about it.
Grow Data Skills: To my leadership, be it my manager or a skip manager, that
Grow Data Skills: you have staffed me in this project, I need to work on it, I need to expedite it, but I'm not very much clear about the requirement. I am, following all the Slack channels, I am looking at all the conversation, going into the meetings, but
Grow Data Skills: still things are not getting clarified. I tried to reach out the project manager engagement managers, but didn't get the clarity. So, in that case, they can pitch in and maybe have the right set of people in a meeting and describe the things that what actually need to be done, okay? So, this is what I have…
Grow Data Skills: like, followed. Earlier, I was also very much dependent on my manager that he will set up a call with me and tell me, hey, just do this thing and do that part. But now, once you are on a little bit senior position, you have to own things as well, you need to chase people as well to get the clarity.
Ravi Shekhawat: Whenever you get into… new domains. Like, when you switch a company and the business is entirely new,
Ravi Shekhawat: There is a rhythm to the business, and we can see that rhythm in the pipelines, right?
Ravi Shekhawat: So, how do you understand all that context? What is your go-to strategy for a new business?
Grow Data Skills: My go-to strategy is to talk to people, right? When you are completely new into a company, at least
Grow Data Skills: They are also giving you time, and you also need a time. It's not like maybe from the second, third day itself, I will start contributing, okay? There could be minor contributions based on your past experiences, but if you're understanding their whole product itself, how does it work, their ecosystem.
Grow Data Skills: Right? How the entire business flow, requirement, design, deployment, everything moves on. So, you need a time. So, I do not rely more onto the documentation or the onboarding videos. My first priority is talk to the main people, right? And then, in the second, third day, talk to the people who are working in that team, and try to get as much as technical knowledge with respect to the platform.
Grow Data Skills: with respect to the process, right? And at least by… after spending a week of time, you can simply ask your manager itself that, to at least
Grow Data Skills: assign you in a particular project where you can shadow them. I mean, whoever is the data engineer, solution engineer working closely on that project, at least you can shadow, and always be in touch with them that even, right, you can contribute on a minor
Grow Data Skills: fix or minor development tasks, that gives you the broader exposure. You get a chance to deep dive into the codebase, you get a chance to deep dive into the whole CI-CD setup, or the way they are raising the pull request, everything, okay? So that is my personal approach that I love
Grow Data Skills: to basically talk to people, get the understandings, and as soon as I can get myself starved into some working sessions or some contributions, that helps me to pick up the things very, very faster.
Ravi Shekhawat: Thank you so much, Isha.
Grow Data Skills: Cool, thank you.
Grow Data Skills: Next is Urwashi.
Grow Data Skills: Hiyoroshi.
Grow Data Skills: Hello?
Grow Data Skills: Hey, Roshi, can you hear me?
Grow Data Skills: I'm not able to hear you, Rishi.
Urvashi Ghore: Hello?
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, I can hear you now.
Urvashi Ghore: Okay. Hi, Shashank. I want to tell you that I am already working.
Urvashi Ghore: As a QEA with Selenium, but .
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Urvashi Ghore: to switch my domain to data engineering, and that's why I joined this course, and I wanted to ask if the projects included in this course will be enough to help me switch to a data engineering role, either within my current company or in another company.
Grow Data Skills: Yes, they will be, because, if you have, I mean, slightly gone through with the project problem statement. So, first of all, I have personally used
Grow Data Skills: my learnings, and the kind of architecture patterns I have been building for a very long time, and whatever is going on in the modern data engineering. So, based on that one, I have designed those problem statements, and they're a full-fledged project, not like…
Grow Data Skills: okay, I have some source, and I have written the Spark application, I will consume the data, and just stored it, and now this is a pipeline.
Grow Data Skills: So, you'll be working on the complete lifecycle of the pipeline, where you'll be looking at the whole design, the trade-off.
Grow Data Skills: the different architecture patterns, and then the CI CD setup, data quality checks, unit testing, code coverage, right? We are going to do each and every aspect of it for every single project we have.
Grow Data Skills: And obviously, working on the good projects, again, more towards the AI aspects, building the rack pipelines, which are a very hot and common topic of discussions as well, that how do you work with these things, how do you deploy, right, and scale it, etc. So, every project you'll be working on this course, Urvashi, is
Grow Data Skills: Going to help you at a very good level to even make a transition in your current company, or even if you go for any lateral hiring move.
Urvashi Ghore: Okay, okay, Shishang, thank you.
Grow Data Skills: Alright.
Grow Data Skills: Next is Akul.
Akul Solanki: Yes, hello. Yes, hi, Sushan, can you hear me?
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, I can hear you.
Akul Solanki: Yeah, thanks, yeah, it was a good start today, yeah, thank you so much for that.
Grow Data Skills: U.
Akul Solanki: Yeah, my question is, like, you know, being a SQL developer, what I see, like, you know, every time we get any new project, definitely the scope is clear, because what we are building is… would be within MSSQL. Now, if we talk about data engineering, then we do have many RDBMS and many things out there, right? Postgres, MySQL, MongoDB.
Akul Solanki: So, let's say I'm working as a data engineering company, so…
Akul Solanki: would it be like they, from starting, they are working on only one RDBMS, or maybe that could be, you know, according to the project that we are getting? And if we are getting different projects, let's say, my expertise in MSScript.
Akul Solanki: Now, what is happening? I'm getting projects in other SQL RDBMS, so how exactly I can approach that? Like, how can I comprehend all this stuff?
Grow Data Skills: Correct, correct. So, see, the number one question is, in the beginning, let's say I mentioned there are RDBMS, there are NoSQL databases as well. So, in the design architectures, and when you actually try to set up anything, these questions are definitely going to come, okay?
Grow Data Skills: So, with respect to, I mean, the proper choice of the database, it actually depends on certain points.
Grow Data Skills: The number one point is what your business use case is demanding, right? Business use case with respect to the technical point of view, okay? So, for an example.
Grow Data Skills: let's say you have created a, like, application, and once you log in, right, into a particular website, what happens? There is a session management. For every specific user, there will be one dedicated session getting created, right?
Grow Data Skills: And once you are in the browser, you open the same URL on the 10 tabs, you will be logged in inside that one, because same session ID is somehow being used, right, to establish that particular connection.
Grow Data Skills: So now, if you look at this kind of implementation, right? So here, what is going to be your priority, correct? Look at from the design perspective.
Grow Data Skills: as soon as… there is a particular session ID, I received it from the API payload.
Grow Data Skills: there should be a database where I can make a lookup in a constant time, like O of one search kind of complexity, right? So, in this case, what kind of database is a very good fit for me, right? I know MongoDB is there, I know MySQL is there, I know RDBMS is there.
Grow Data Skills: So now if you feel, okay, MySQL
Grow Data Skills: It is also a database. Let's say whenever user is logging in, I will simply maintain the session ID as my primary key, and will store its detail in the MySQL.
Grow Data Skills: But now, think about it, the search part, when you will write the filter query, again, it's a row-based database, right? So, you have to iterate on the row levels, and then you need to find out the right particular key and filter out, but you know how much time you are wasting here in this one. Whereas, if you have any database.
Grow Data Skills: Right? For an example, the DynamoDB, right? In the AWS, we have a DynamoDB, which is a key-value based. So there, you can have a session ID as a key, and the entire user-related detail as a value. So now, when you are following this
Grow Data Skills: data storage pattern, right? So that's what I was saying. The choice of the database
Grow Data Skills: is actually going to depend on the technical demand of your business or the architecture you are building. The kind of use case you are going to solve, based on that one, you will be able to try to benchmark and find the right fit database. That is number one. Second is definitely, when you do the benchmarking, you always
Grow Data Skills: try to look at the performance side as well, and you always try to look at the costing part as well. That is the second factor. And the third factor, there are a lot of times various enterprise-level use cases which have been solved by the different
Grow Data Skills: database enterprises already. For an example, in many of the companies which are, let's say, working heavily on the financial data, right, you will see Oracle is coming into the picture a lot, right?
Akul Solanki: Right.
Grow Data Skills: Because…
Grow Data Skills: It is also a transactional database, but apart from just the database, right, they are giving the entire enterprise solutions as well. I'm talking with respect to my experience at Expedia. So, there.
Grow Data Skills: we… I was building the one checkout platform where all the financial data, right, of the user bookings will flow, right? And it will get dumped into the Oracle, which was our financial database. It was used by the finance analysts, chartered accountants. Why? Because
Grow Data Skills: Just not the database, but they were giving the complete enterprise solutions, where the finance analysts can write their financial rules to generate the debit credit entries, so that we can make a final supplier payout.
Grow Data Skills: So, this is how these benchmarking and write choice of the database is being made. And your last question, if you have expertise in one, how do you pick up the another one which you haven't worked on?
Grow Data Skills: So, idea is very simple. As I said, the foundational layer, right, for all these databases is going to be the same. Select will be select in all these databases. Group by will be grouped by in all these databases, right?
Grow Data Skills: The only thing which you might keep on seeing frequently getting changed, that is the data types.
Grow Data Skills: Right, their definitions till some extent, functions, how do you call them, how do you use them? A bit more on the creation of stored procedures and the triggers, but 70% layer of the SQL is completely same across these databases.
Akul Solanki: Hardly few syntaxes would be changed, maybe.
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, yeah.
Akul Solanki: All right, and one last question. What about the CI-CD, part? Like.
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, so we will have that. We will, like, do it in the project. That will come in the project itself, like, having GitHub, GitHub Actions, and once you commit your changes in the Git, how your entire codebase goes into the cloud, infra, everything, you will have in the project part.
Akul Solanki: Okay, perfect. That is… Shashang, yeah, thank you so much.
Grow Data Skills: Thank you, thank you.
Grow Data Skills: Next is Gita.
Grow Data Skills: Hey, Geeta.
Grow Data Skills: Gita, can you hear me?
Grow Data Skills: Hello?
Grow Data Skills: Okay, mehir? Nick?
Geetha Karthik: Am I audible?
Grow Data Skills: Hey, Geeta, I can hear you now. Okay, your name Karthik? Geetha Kartik, okay. Hey, I can hear you now.
Geetha Karthik: It's my brother's computer, it take my brother.
Grow Data Skills: Oh, no worries, no worries.
Geetha Karthik: My name is Jai Chamber.
Geetha Karthik: My question is, is it covered in future, like, migration of, on-premises to cloud, any example or, like, procedure?
Geetha Karthik: from Oracle to Databricks, how it will be done.
Grow Data Skills: Oh, no, can you repeat, like, the Oracle to Databricks, like, the migration of the data? That's… that's something you're asking for.
Geetha Karthik: Yeah, yes.
Grow Data Skills: I mean, it was not in my plan. I mean, I had a plan to touch upon various data pipeline patterns, but obviously not on-premises, because obviously I don't have that infra, but if you want that, I can definitely include one problem
Grow Data Skills: statement where, let's say, I have a database on the AWS, and
Grow Data Skills: that something… entire data I want to migrate on Databricks data tables, right? So we can definitely work on that problem statement, not a problem. We… I will include that.
Geetha Karthik: Yeah, because we have that scenario, but I'm not aware of that, how they…
Grow Data Skills: Like, migration projects are very common, right? So, we will discuss that, and the approach of, like, because when you are on the mid-senior, senior positions, when you go into the interviews, these questions comes up. When you actually do the migration project, instead of
Grow Data Skills: The technical approach, the interviewer is much more interested to hear about your business approach, right? Business approach that, like, you are working for a client, how you are going to take his entire migration journey. How will you analyze the critical workloads? Because first, we'll focus on that one.
Grow Data Skills: So that you can see the broader picture of your product, whether your product will be able to support this entire migration or not. If some features are missing, first you will raise that request, get it done, and then you will pick that specific
Grow Data Skills: workload, and that, too, in the iterative manner. First, you will pick the particular workload which is least critical for the migration, so that you have migrated it, and then our QA team, their QA team, will do the entire data quality checks, and then you will be running it for one week or two weeks on their actual
Grow Data Skills: let's say production data in parallel with their actual data pipeline, so that we are matching the numbers. If everything goes fine, then you will start migrating aggressively each and every workload.
Grow Data Skills: So, I'm telling you that in the interviews, both of the aspects will be touched. How do you understand the whole
Grow Data Skills: The process of the migration from the business point of view, and from the technical point of view.
Geetha Karthik: Okay.
Geetha Karthik: Cool.
Grow Data Skills: Next is Mihir.
Grow Data Skills: Hey, Mil, I have given you the access, please, you can ask a question.
Mihir Saiya: Yeah, first of all, good afternoon, sir.
Grow Data Skills: Hey, good afternoon, man, thank you.
Mihir Saiya: As I have asked this question earlier, and on a Discord, and you have also commented on that, but I wanted more clarity on that. So, as a 4-year folk who, doesn't have any…
Grow Data Skills: Sorry, sorry, sorry, as in?
Mihir Saiya: Fortier engineering tool.
Grow Data Skills: Fourth year engineering student, okay?
Mihir Saiya: I haven't done as much, major projects and wanted to make a career in data engineering. So, around 5 to 6 months later, placements will come in our college. So, my question was how, how to target the entry-level roles.
Grow Data Skills: So, see, Mayor, at your level, at the stage you are at, right, I think I also mentioned, at your experience level, currently, the problem solving is going to play a very important role, because you are a fresher, right? Even they are going to get you hired for a data engineering role.
Grow Data Skills: If you are mentioning good data engine tech stack projects, that is a good-to-have thing for them from your side, right?
Grow Data Skills: But they are going to judge you mostly, mostly on your…
Grow Data Skills: the freshest level perspective, right? Testing you on your DSA skills, right? The problem solving, Python skills, testing you on the SQL skills, right? So these three things should be your main, main priority to work on regressively, right? After that one, right, whatever you are going to learn from this particular program, like, specifically Spark.
Grow Data Skills: And the data warehouse is a bit of cloud, and the airflow, right?
Grow Data Skills: You will… you can mention those things, right, and the projects we'll be doing around it. That will put a very, very good impact on your profile, and it will give them the confidence as well that this guy has already done some sort of good, projects on its own, and it will… it will create a good impression as well.
Mihir Saiya: And, my another doubt was that, for, suppose I'm targeting for a future MBA master's, where, I will be doing master's around, 2 to 3 years later, after working, some prior job. So, how can MBA plus DE roles can, combine in this.
Grow Data Skills: Hmm, I mean…
Grow Data Skills: That will be helpful if, after completing the MBA, if you are targeting the TPM type of role, like technical program managers, right? In that case, this will be pretty much helpful, but apart from that, if you are targeting any other role, then this de-learning is not going to help you. But, yeah, TPM role.
Grow Data Skills: if you are working for any company which is, like, their data team, or a company which is related to data and AI, then whatever learning you have brought with respect to the data engineering, right, with your MBA skills and targeting the TPM role, then it's pretty much good. Apart from that, if your target is something else, then no value of this thing.
Mihir Saiya: Okay, thank you.
Grow Data Skills: Next is Weibo.
Grow Data Skills: Hey, Rebel.
Vaibhav: Yeah, honey.
Grow Data Skills: Hello.
Vaibhav: Yeah, hello?
Vaibhav: Am I audible.
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, yeah, I can hear you. Feel free to ask your question.
Vaibhav: Yeah, I have one question, like, for a data engineer, are you seeing more projects, demands and volume coming from the AWS side, or from the Azure side?
Grow Data Skills: see, if it's product-based, and if it is startups, scale startups. Majority of the time, I have seen AWS.
Grow Data Skills: Whereas, if it's consulting companies and service-based companies, I have seen majority Azure is coming into the picture. But a very important factor to understand when you talk about any of three cloud platforms.
Grow Data Skills: All three of them have created same type of services, right? They're solving common purpose. The differences are with respect to the integration, the bit of performance, a bit of costing, and 5-10% changes from the UI implementation perspective. Example, if you want to do the…
Grow Data Skills: let's say, data warehousing on cloud. So AWS has Redshift, Azure has Synapse, and GCP has BigQuery. All three of them are solving common purpose, data warehousing on cloud. So once you master any one cloud platform at any point of time.
Grow Data Skills: So, if you get opportunity to work on any different cloud platform, it will be just a one-on-one mapping, right? You just need to find that what you were working on AWS, what is the exact alternative for that on Azure, and the vice versa.
Vaibhav: Yeah, thanks, Hasan.
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Grow Data Skills: Next is, Razak.
Grow Data Skills: Hello?
Abdul Razzak Khan: Hi, sir, am I audible?
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, I can hear you.
Abdul Razzak Khan: Yeah, thank you for the opportunity. And, my question is, in regards to SQL.
Abdul Razzak Khan: like, I am someone, like, if I'm, like, I'm doing MySQL for now. I'm, started doing that. So, my thing is, is I wanted to know one of the, like, MySQL, MongoDB, or any other, which I could do, simultaneously.
Abdul Razzak Khan: And, like, what you're teaching over here in MySQL, I can, like, simultaneously do on the other one as well, where, there is not slight difference in the other, this system. So there's a bigger difference, so that I can, catch hold that thing earlier, in my… this.
Abdul Razzak Khan: when I get a job in that domain, so it will be easier for me, to, do that thing if it's in MongoDB, so it will be easier for me.
Grow Data Skills: I totally lost your question, Aja. Can you explain last two parts one more time?
Grow Data Skills: I was trying to understand, like, what you were expecting, but yeah, please repeat one more time.
Abdul Razzak Khan: like, something like MySQL, I want to know, that that is more relevant in the, companies, or like MongoDB or anything else, and that is more relevant in the company, like, mostly they use.
Abdul Razzak Khan: use in the company, and it is more different from MySQL.
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Grow Data Skills: So, see, here…
Grow Data Skills: when you talk about SQL, so that is irrespective of any data… the database, correct? So, the thing which you are learning here, right, that is SQL part I'm talking about, that is applicable on your RDB MS, and most importantly, right, on your data warehouses, okay? Because when you will be working with Snowflake, or the Databricks delta tables, or Iceberg tables.
Grow Data Skills: hoodie tables, or the Redshift, Synapse, BigQuery, whatever it is.
Grow Data Skills: This entire SQL learning, you are going to apply there for any sort of analytical things.
Grow Data Skills: Now, a question about the relevancy. So, in the companies, there is nothing about a relevancy. All the databases which are presented there, they are relevant in their respective use cases, and companies are using them
Grow Data Skills: accordingly. When you go into the interviews.
Grow Data Skills: no one asks you that, okay, give me the answers as per the MySQL, and he's asking, give me answers as per the Postgres, etc. They don't do it in that way, right? If they're focusing, right, on your SQL knowledge, it is going to be irrespective of your database's understanding. Database understanding has a different layer, where we talked about the choice, the architecture, the trade-off.
Grow Data Skills: That comes based on the business technical decision and what kind of use case you are trying to solve. I think similar thing I explained to another guy who asked the similar question.
Abdul Razzak Khan: Okay, thank you. Just one last thing, like, if you are joining in a company, and, they do, do database work or everything in a particular way, and you have been taught in a different way.
Abdul Razzak Khan: So you have to go through all those things that have been done in that company previously, and then get a hang of it, and then do it as per their choice of work.
Grow Data Skills: Hmm. So, it happens, obviously. A lot of time, let's say.
Grow Data Skills: I mean, if you are in a company, so taking an example, right, in Expedia, we were using Confluent Kafka. So now, if Expedia is using Confluent Kafka, right, for all their stream-based ingestion through Kafka, so now there is no point that
Grow Data Skills: I am going to bring something else, like a Rabbit MQ, or the managed Kafka on the AWS, or managed Kafka on Azure, because they have a set of standards, which they have already created, so I'm going to leverage that. Similarly, maybe for the CICD process.
Grow Data Skills: Until and unless there is a very different use case, where whatever
Grow Data Skills: Expedia has been following so far.
Grow Data Skills: I mean, that is not… is the right fit for the particular use case we are trying to solve. And that's what we did, like, I mean, there was one component where…
Grow Data Skills: the one checkout platform we were building. So, there we did a benchmarking between the ScyllaDB, MongoDB, and Cassandra, right? Because we had to ingest our data, and we had to expose the GraphQL APIs on top of it. So, after doing all that benchmarking.
Grow Data Skills: we chose the ScyllaDB there, okay? And that's how we were using it, and we were working on it. And prior to that one.
Grow Data Skills: ScyllaDB was not even in the picture in the Expedia ecosystem. None of the team was using it. So that's how it is coming up, and that's how it comes up, right? When you are working in an organization, so a lot of time, whatever.
Grow Data Skills: standard follow process they have set up. We, majority of the time, go ahead with that one, until unless we have to take a new decision as per the business criticality.
Abdul Razzak Khan: Okay, thank you very much. And, lastly, this, do you use, visualization like Power BI in your, this.
Grow Data Skills: No, for data engineering.
Abdul Razzak Khan: me.
Grow Data Skills: No, no, no, no. For data engineering, not needed at all, right?
Abdul Razzak Khan: Hoping learned that it's fine, right?
Grow Data Skills: Yeah, not at all. I'm not going to say that go learn Tableau, Power BI, not at all. Because…
Grow Data Skills: as a data engineer, our responsibilities are 99% very differently. If in any company you are handling the dashboarding as well, handling the pipelining, that role is not 100% data engineering then.
Abdul Razzak Khan: Okay, makes sense. Thanks a lot.
Grow Data Skills: Alright, yeah.
Grow Data Skills: Akash, can you please share the topics we need to cover Python to get ourselves ready for upcoming sessions? So, Akash, for that one, you have already got the access of free Python course, okay? So, just go through that one, because that will be sufficient enough for the practical exercises we will be doing.
Grow Data Skills: Next is Anand.
Grow Data Skills: Hey, Anand.
Anand: Hello?
Grow Data Skills: Hello? Okay. Yeah, I can hear you, Anand.
Anand: Hey, Shoshan. So, I'm currently working as a data engineer, and I have around 8 months of experience after college.
Anand: And my work is mainly focused on Snowflake, where I prepare design views and reporting views for further gold layer analytics.
Anand: And I've recently also finished the Snowpro certification.
Grow Data Skills: Okay.
Anand: I'm a little concerned that if this the only work experience I have.
Anand: It might make switching roles difficult.
Grow Data Skills: So your overall experience is 8 months as of now, right?
Anand: Yeah.
Anand: And this.
Grow Data Skills: Yup.
Anand: only production-grade work I'm doing in my team. It is a CX team.
Grow Data Skills: So that's totally fine, right? There is no concerns about that, because when you talk about the snowflake in itself, right?
Grow Data Skills: a very top-quality, enterprise-level, right, entire analytics platform itself, okay? So, although your use case is slightly different, you are, like, working more on the analytical side of it, but obviously, you are going to get a good learnings
Grow Data Skills: From here, so maybe the typical ingestion process you are doing end-to-end in the Snowflake itself, that you can maybe portray
Grow Data Skills: in a different way, like leveraging these architectural component and the pipeline pattern components we will be covering. So, instead of just showing everything you have done through the snowflake, you can put it that way itself. And, to be very honest, with 8 months of experience, 1 year of…
Grow Data Skills: industrial experience, even if you go for a data engineering interviews, right?
Grow Data Skills: 70% of weightage is going to be given on your SQL skill.
Grow Data Skills: Python problem solving, whatever you know with respect to Spark, whatever you know with respect to the data modeling, right? And whatever you are, like, putting with respect to, let's say, cloud, etc, they are not going to grill you at all. I'm telling you based on my experiences.
Grow Data Skills: When I interviewed at Paytm as well, with having 2 years of experience, they simply tested me on Python, SQL, Spark.
Grow Data Skills: whatever Spark internals, I knew, whatever I knew about Spark DataFrame, data sets, etc, and in the managerial realm, all about my past project development experiences, what I did, what challenges I faced, right? So for entry-level fresher roles, although you might be doing a different work, the expectation does not go on a very high level, that we are expecting all modern data engineering
Grow Data Skills: Architecture from this guy.
Anand: Okay, a little continuation. So, if I may be switching a year later, so wherever it will be.
Anand: Won't they be expecting some, like, main data engineer work, like pipeline work at a production-grade setup?
Grow Data Skills: They… they will be. So, yeah, that's why… that's why I mentioned, right, that whatever problem statements you are solving, just on the…
Grow Data Skills: snowflake level. Why not to leverage those problem statements
Grow Data Skills: and put it in your profile or resume in a way that that was completely designed on the AWS, let's say, right? So that is also a better way to represent yourself, because the AWS knowledge, the data engineering tech stack framework knowledge, you are going to get from this program, right? So after having that knowledge, it will be easy for you to migrate those snowflake problem statements
Grow Data Skills: completely with these, modern data engineering architecture patterns, not just keeping everything on the snowflake. So that's what I'm saying.
Anand: Okay. Thank you.
Grow Data Skills: Yep.
Grow Data Skills: Okay, it is, cool. Is WSL on Windows is enough to work with Kafka and other tools, or do we need…
Grow Data Skills: So, for that, we will be doing the free tier setup. Confluent, Kafka provides free tier setup, Snowflake, etc. So, wherever setup-related things will come up, I will already explain it in the session, right? So don't worry about it. I will already, do it in the session, okay?
Grow Data Skills: Alright, then I… think we are done for the… today's doubts as well, so…
Grow Data Skills: Cool, let's meet tomorrow, guys, and as I said, the today's material, content, and everything, I will be uploading in the LMS after 2-3 hours.
Grow Data Skills: Okay? So you can practice it, and let's meet tomorrow, and we will continue from where we left. Okay? Thank you guys, thanks for joining, bye-bye, take care.